is of at least one faction of the Sillucids
and ruling on their own again
with autonomy in their own land.
And if you wanna be in our good graces,
visit badbooksofthebible.com
where you can subscribe to get our
impeccable notes with our impeccable sources.
The impeccable.
You can follow us on Twitter.
Visit a link directly to our ancient based show page
so it makes it easy to share with friends.
And best of all is you will not miss.
episode. We've got some exciting content coming your way in the next few weeks.
I'm Jamie Bennett and I'm Joel Miller and you've been listening to bad
books of the Bible. A production of Ancient Faith Radio. Come back next week when
we find out just how convoluted politics can get.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever.
You're listening to ancient...
faithradio.com.
demons and saints. In our time many year into break free of the prison of a flat
secular materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this
spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every
day life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show, focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of the
and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind
throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers.
Dragon Slayers, you are listening
to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
the Reverend Doctor, is with me
from Lafayette, Louisiana.
Very, Reverend Doctor.
Oh, excuse me, the very Reverend Doctor.
Can I throw out my big title as well?
The Reverend.
I'm sorry.
And I'm Father Edges Steven, David in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
Just like the voice of Steve just said,
Matushka Trudy is taking your calls tonight.
Our engineer extraordinaire.
And we're gonna get to those
in the second part of our show.
Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners
with help from Theoria School of Film Making.
Theoria School of Film Making is the first
Fourth, the dock.
film school. The primary instructor is Jonathan Jackson, a faithful orthodox
Christian speaker, writer, and five-time Emmy award winner. To learn more about
Theoria, please visit TheoriaFilm.org that's TH-E-O-R-I-A film.org.
Because of the Theoria School of Film Making that like Kurosawa, I make mad films.
Okay, I don't make films, but if I did, they'd have a samurai.
All right.
That was for our Canadian listeners.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It took me, it took my brain like a couple of seconds to realize that you were quoting a
certain band of fully clothed males, fully clothed males.
Yeah.
So this evening we're going to wrap up our three part series on the Fall of Man.
Tonight is about the Tower of Babel, which we first learn about in Genesis chapter 11.
the people who first heard.
Genesis 11 weren't hearing this for the first time.
In fact, they already knew the story,
but most of us probably don't.
So that's where we're beginning tonight.
The context into which Genesis 11 was speaking.
So what is that context, Father?
The olden times.
Back in the day, the before times.
Yeah.
Back in the day when the group was cool and I wasn't in it.
The way back the before time.
Yeah.
Yeah, so one of our major Fosai tonight is going to be the fact that sort of like the creation of the world and the flood, the story that's told in Genesis 11, the first part of it at least, it's not that long, about the tower of Babel.
is also a biblical retelling of
of an event that was sort of common knowledge
in the ancient Near East.
And people are probably more aware of the first two, right?
Like it probably seems obvious to most people
that like yeah, these different cultures
would have different stories about the creation
of the world, right?
Or how it came into being.
And if you've done any reading at all
about the ancient world or ancient mythology
or the Bible in comparison.
literature. One of the first things you find out about is the fact that there are flood stories
everywhere in the world. But so this one is a little more specific. And therefore I think a lot
of people haven't necessarily made the connection between this story and actual events that everyone
one would have known about and
that are historical events, right?
So we kind of start with, okay, so what is even being talked about in this story,
which is sort of a longish paragraph?
Yeah, it's not.
Chapter 11 of Genesis.
It's not a big piece of text.
Yeah.
And then that text just kind of moves on from there.
I mean, we consider that, you know, the flood proper, right, is Genesis 6 through 9.
Right. And if you include as we would and as people have heard us do in the last couple of weeks include like cane and his genealogy in there with the flood, then you're talking about Genesis 4 through 9.
Right. This is not the whole chapter.
chapter. This is a good probably more than half in terms of text. Slightly more than half
of chapter 11 of Genesis is actually Abraham's genealogy.
Yes, chapter 12. Yeah, I mean the tower Babel story is verses one through nine of Genesis 11 and then
Then the rest is genealogy stuff. Yeah
Leading actually it's a genealogy of Tara Abraham's father technically, but yeah, yeah, just so we don't get
Oh, I'm actually
In a chat box somewhere
To go in the cell
But so what is and you know, there's kind of a thing right we treat this
We've become used to treating this partially because most folks are big fans of reading
genealogies.
We treat this as like, oh, well, here's this story that's in between some genealogy stuff
that we skim, right?
But all of the genealogies, and we've seen this several times, right?
Already, just in the early chapters of Genesis, all of these genealogies will like hit pause
occasionally and
have small stories and pieces of information in them, right?
Like Enic being taken up into heaven, right?
Right.
Which is in Seth's genealogy, right?
Or some of the stuff we talked about last time with Cain's genealogy, right?
Yeah.
Things that they invented in Strait of Lamek, right?
And this just feeds into, you know, I can't remember which episode it was now, but we
talked about history and what history is in the pre-modern era.
the story of a people and
The narrative of people, a lot of it is going to be genealogies, particularly of kings,
and then certain exploits related to some of those kings or events that surround them
and bring context to the story of that particular people.
And that's what's going on here.
Right.
So, this being only nine verses, right?
You know, there's kind of a fuzzy line where we say, like, oh, well, if it's three or
four verses that's
just part of the genealogy, but if it's nine verses, then this is separate from the genealogies.
Right. That's kind of arbitrary distinction.
Right, because again, there's not such a thing as verses back there.
Yes, or chapter breaks, chapter.
Any of that, right? So this is a story that is now nine verses, but that gives you an idea of the
the leg that's in this genealogical material.
And so the easiest way I think to start getting into this in terms of identifying what this story is about is to start with Bable.
Right. This is famously the Tower of Bable.
And so, I put this in our inaccessible show notes.
I put the actual Kadeiform of the Sumerian...
name for for Bable right which is sorry everybody I'll put it if you're watching on YouTube
I will put it in the YouTube chat so you can actually see the uniform. YouTube will yes I
did this last time and it worked so everybody can now see it if you're watching on YouTube. Hey
YouTube people. All 21 of you.
Tubers? Yeah.
So, um, and hey, it worked on Facebook too. Just FYI Facebook listeners. Yeah, we'll let you
So exciting. Yes. Yes. Yeah, it's crazy. I can't guarantee that people's computers will display it, but it's working. Oh, yeah, that's the other mind. Yeah. Yeah, that would be the other issue. Yeah, it works on mine. I don't know. Anyway.
Yeah. Yeah, and that it's to marry it. It's basically pronounced good or couldn't
uh diggerock
Okay. Which as we all know is means literally gate of the gods. Right. So it's made up of four symbols for the folks who can't see, which may be everybody, but the people who can't see the good day or for even though father energy is posting it.
And people who won't be listening live who probably won't see it.
But it's a bait.
It's four Cuneiform symbols.
The first one is basically a pictograph of a gate.
That's the gun or the couldn't.
And then the second symbol looks kind of like a star
on purpose and it's pronounced D-Gar,
which is the word for a god, or the symbol for a god.
And the third symbol for a god looks like a star.
Yeah.
Yep.
All of this is a sci-fi pictographic.
I'm sorry.
I'm shocked.
I'm shocked, I tell you.
And then the third symbol is what's pronounced rock.
That's essentially to make the word God what we would call in Greek or Latin a genitive.
So that's the of the essentially.
Right.
So that it's gate of the gods.
then the fourth symbol is a symbol that we've seen before.
Yes, I recognize it from previous notes.
From the last show.
Is sort of a diamond shape
by the exterior that denotes it as a place name.
Yeah.
And it, cause it looks like a little walled city
or something like that.
So it's like the place that is the gate of the gods, right?
And the Akkadian name is Bob Ely.
Bye, being gay.
Ely being gods, you could probably detect the L, Ely, right?
That's a midi group.
Submitted group there.
So there's a bunch of debate because sumerologists, like everybody else, have to write dissertations
and publish journal articles.
As to which of these, the Sumerian form or the Akkadian form came first.
which is a translation of the other because it doesn't sound like each other.
It's not a-
It's not a lone word either way. It's an actual, what they call a calc, C-A-L-Q-U-E, where
you translate the parts and create a new word out of that.
Right. Like, you know, everybody calls the town red stick and then change it to Baton Rouge
to be fancy.
But, in this case, the reason for that argument is that this is the only known case of
a place name in Mesopotamia.
where the Sumerian and Acadian names for the place are translations.
Right, not like a transliteration,
but actually they translated it from one language into the other so that it would mean the same thing.
So that then raised the question, which came first, everybody's like, great,
now I have a journal article to write.
And things could go on his plan.
But
Both of them mean, right? One is the Sumerian form and one of them is the Akkadian
and their four Semitic form of Gate of the Gods. How we get from Bob Ely to Babylon is through Greek
because the Greek transliterated the
the Acadian as Babylon.
So if you know the Greek alphabet and you're reading the Greek Old Testament or the New Testament in Greek and you come to Babylon, you will instantly recognize it because it's Babylon.
Yeah, right.
So, um, and so that just gets translated into English
according to standard like conventions, right?
Yeah.
It's beta alpha beta.
Yippsalone, Lambda,
Oincron, new, right? Yeah, so yeah, Babel equals Babelon.
Right, that's a really important identification to make here. These are not two different places as far as the biblical Texas concerned.
Right, right. And the place that should confirm that to you is right there in Genesis 11.
Because even though we brush over this when we read the story, it actually says that they set out to build a city and a tower.
Right. Not just the tower. Right. So it's the tower of Bable, meaning it's the tower actually Ziggurat of the city of Bobbile, aka Babylon.
Now when you get to all that said, when you get to verse 9, right, this is the letter
So at the end of the story, the
Hebron text indicates that the name Bavle comes from the Hebrew verb Bilbel.
Right, so it's presenting an etymology, like you know it says in the ESV,
therefore its name was called Babel because they're the Lord confused the language of all the earth.
Right, so it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's coming from the Hebrew billbell. Now.
It is a generally true phenomenon that ancient literature is full of bogus etymologies.
Yeah, it's true.
The reliable, you know, philological discipline of etymology is pretty much a modern thing.
Ancient peoples did not seem to know how this worked.
In fact, the idea that languages that were not mutually comprehensive...
at the time actually had a common, you know,
ear language was not a thing that occurred to most people either.
Right, right. And so it was sort of whatever was close,
sometimes even they're working in their own language,
ancient Greek literature, classical Greek literature is like super terrible about this.
Yeah. It's just sort of whatever word seems similar.
Yeah. One of the famous ones in Plato's Republic is him saying that
that decals.
is derived from D.K. to cut.
Wow.
Which it's not.
Yeah.
Oh my god.
All this stuff.
Yeah.
It's interesting they have this idea
that some words are derived from others,
but they so often get that wrong.
Yeah.
And they just try to break them apart.
And I mean, you could do that in English very easily too.
Right.
People do it all lie.
Yeah.
Being the classic example, right.
So that said, right.
That set is very...
And a lot of scholars will just say, well, like, okay, this is bogus, right?
I don't think that that's what this is, that this is an ancient bad etymology.
I would argue that this is deliberate.
Okay.
For one thing, a cadian in Hebrew are not that different.
Right.
and here's here's
how well the two pieces of Bob Ely, right? The the
Acadian name that Bavill comes from. How well that's held on?
Bob Ely, I mean, it's probably pronounced slightly differently, but
basically means gate of the gods in Arabic. Right, like
modern Arabic. Yeah, I don't have that much Arabic knowledge, but
I don't know right now.
They're speakers.
Yeah, we're all told to be this.
Yes.
Well placed people who would know right and again, it's I'm sure it's pronounced a little differently, but basically like they could look at that and say yeah, right
so
It seems to me to be a difficult argument
to say
That whatever writer
Editor wherever you want to place this in the process of the Torah as we have it now coming together, right?
Right.
Um.
Whoever that was at any stage
Didn't honestly know what Babel came from number one Bob L
Right
but
But actually thought it came from Bill Bell which
Barely resembles it, hmm, right
So I would argue this is a deliberate thing
Thank you.
This is deliberate.
They're making a comment.
Yes, he's making a comment.
This is not the place of the gate of the gods.
This is the place of confusion.
Yeah, it's a correction being.
And so it's more like how the ancient Hebrews
changed Baal Zabool, which went sort of high Lord
bail to balls of
boob more to the flies. Right. Right. It's a joke. It's
trash talk. Yes, which is a reference to X-Rumant. Okay,
anyone didn't know because that's where the flies all gather
together. Right. Right. So it's more like that. Right. So this
is a deliberate comment being made about Babylon. So what we
get even from just this initial sort of
cursory look at this little story here in Genesis 11 is that
this is a text that is commenting on the founding of Babylon.
Yeah. Right. Right.
So what's actually up with the founding of Babylon?
So we have a really good idea of when Babylon was founded.
Yeah, which is kind of weird for
events in the ancient world that yes and this is a very ancient world this is a
nice idea this is not just like pre when Moses lived regardless of how early
you think Moses lived this is pre when Abraham lived right this before the
or three period okay so this is way back right none of the old testament was
written in the time we're talking about yeah this is over four thousand years
I'm just like, how?
Yes.
But.
what we know from archaeology and what we know from ancient writers matches up
almost perfectly which never happens. This like never happens. So archaeologically
the earliest reference we have to Babylon comes from a tablet so these clay
fire tablets that Kineiform was written on.
are nigh indestructible. Right? You get breaks and gaps sometimes. That's why I said nigh.
Right? But it takes a lot. Right? The average one, you could, if you threw it at your floor, it would
make a dent in your floor. It would not like shatter. Right? Yeah. That's why they've survived for
all these thousands of years because they're very sturdy.
And most of the ones where you see breaks, like if you're reading and you see breaks in the text, usually there's a tablet missing or it's not that the whole tablet has gotten destroyed.
It's that something's happened. There's a big chip out of the front that where we can't read the writing.
Hmm, right.
Some chip has got knocked off of it.
Usually it like, you know, the city was conquered 14 times, you know,
leveled, burned to the ground, and, you know, the tap...
it got chipped. So we're all on the way. Right. Like that level. And we should say that most
of these tablets that are out there are not cool things like the founding of Babylon or the
Bale cycle. It's, you know, like, yeah, people's grocery lists and whatever. As far as we know,
because most of them are untranslated. I know we've talked about that on the show before.
Exactly. There's a career out there, people. You just got to get a grant. I would imagine the ratio
of cool stuff to trade docs.
humans is probably roughly the same between the translated and untranslated portions.
But the earliest one of these we have that mentions Babylon is from somewhere in the mid
23rd century BC.
Okay, so that'd be the 2200's BC?
Yes, yeah.
and somewhere in the middle of it.
So, you know, the dead middle would be 22-50.
which is near the end of the reign of Sargon of a cod.
Which is such a great name.
Yeah, not the YouTube dude.
No, no.
The actual image.
Yes.
So, the...
He's called Sargon of a cod.
This will come up again later.
We mentioned this before, right?
Mesopotamia historically...
Pretty much always until...
tell my
times really was divided into northern and southern portions. The southern
portion was Sumer, the northern portion was a cod, right, and we already mentioned
the two languages Sumerian and Acadian and Acadian is Semitic, Sumerian is a
language isolate, meaning it's not related to anything as far as we know.
And so within Mesopotamia, sort of the balance of power through...
out the fourth and third millennia BC sort of went back and forth between Sumerian cities
and Akkadian cities, Sumerian dynasties and Akkadian dynasties of kings. So he's called
Sargon of Akad because he was the head of a major Akkadian dynasty. Right, right, in Akad.
So near the end of his reign, we have it.
tablet that refers to Babylon as a town, not as a city, as a town. So it's sort of a settlement
at this point on the Euphrates River.
Okay. So that's our earliest sort of reference to it being there in terms of trying to date
it's founding that we've got from our modern archaeology.
Okay.
But we have various ancient...
sources where you go through these in order of increasing ancientness. That also give us dates
we can work out. And in a lot of cases, the person whose writings we have say that they're
getting their information from somebody else who's even more ancient than them.
Okay.
So there's some...
But we don't have those sources to check on, right?
We just have to sort of later, but still ancient person.
So the first one to talk about is George Sincelos.
Okay, he's late eighth century.
So late eighth century Byzantine historian, incredibly important.
We've mentioned him on the show before.
And he says he has a very strong, very strong,
access to the writings of this dude Cotesius who we don't know anything about. But he
said he has access to these writings of Cotesius and Cotesius says George St.
Kellos had these ancient Babylonian documents about the founding of Babylon. So this is
is third hand, right? Coming from from George St. Gallows. And
And he dates the founding of Babylon at 2286 BC.
So that's sort of early 23rd century BC.
Right.
Well, if it's there is a town around 2250, then 2286 kind of makes sense.
Is it date for founding?
But George Sakello's did not have that tablet that we're going by.
Right.
I don't have access to that.
He's going from other information.
So a little more ancient than that.
Hey there's a fella.
name Stephen of Byzantium. That's a good solid name. And we know almost nothing about him. Right. That's right. That's why he's called Stephen of Byzantium. But he lived. Right. But he's sort of roughly contemporary with the Emperor St. Justinian. Yeah. He lived in Constantinople.
six century during the reign of St.
Justidian so in the in the six
century.
And he says that Babylon
was founded 1,000 in two years, not 1,000 years.
I know, it's so great.
1,000 in two years.
You almost expect to say, and 13 days before the Siege of Troy, which based on his own dating
of the Siege of Troy, would put it at 2231 BC.
Okay, so we've had three dates now roughly the middle of the 23rd century.
early 23rd century, late-ish, 23rd century BC. Yeah. Yeah. And so then our most sort of
ancient source on this is Pliny or Pliny, but I'm going to say Pliny. It's okay, it's English.
I think that's the British way of doing it is to do a little bit of like constant time.
I've never discussed Pliny with any British people that I can recall.
I may soon have an opportunity to do this. I will verify.
Yeah, check with them. Make another.
Could you say those words?
Chimpanzee, right? Okay.
Aluminum.
So Pliny, who lived in the early second century AD,
This is plenty of the younger by the way everybody because there's an elder plenty to and so he
quotes
this fellow barosis
So barosis is an interesting guy. Unfortunately, we don't actually have barosis as writings. We just have people citing barosis
So barosis
was a third century BC priest of Belmarduk
So he was...
a priest of like Bale and the Babylonian God Marduk in the third century BC during the
Seljukid period in Syria. And so Barosis wrote in Greek and so he sort of wrote down in Greek
at that time sort of Babylonian myths stuff.
about Babylonian worship and sacrifice and sort of wrote that all down in Greek for a Greek audience.
So he was sort of the point of access to ancient Near Eastern religion for the Edith Hamilton
of his day for the Greeks and the Romans. Although he had a lot more of the practical religious stuff
about sacrifice. So that's the only access they had to it. It'd be great if we ever found
and barossa.
because it would be this is treasure trove of information, but we only have places where he gets quoted
by classical authors, but so Pliny quotes him
or sites him as having placed
The founding of Babylon and in this case he doesn't actually say the founding of Babylon
He says that
They began to do astrology at Babylon
on. At that side.
right and for him right we've talked before about how when you read like in the Torah somebody calling
upon the name of the Lord that that's worship right right right for Barosis that seems to have been
doing astrology seems to be have been for him the beginning of religion I see okay right so that kind
of equates it to the religious founding for his.
Stars and Gods again.
Yeah, yeah, I'm shocked
But he places that at 2243 BC
Okay, so then to kind of wrap this up you know our earliest date is 2286 BC the latest is 2231
All these dates are basically within 55 years of each other which you talk in the ancient world that's like
inches away in terms of dating things from the ancient world.
Yes.
is people writing centuries later and our best archaeology from the time.
Yeah, that's a great modern archaeology.
So we can be pretty sure that this is around when Babylon was founded or some major
thing started happening there. Right. Right. Well, there weren't a lot of
major things happening there yet. Yeah. This is what it started.
The astrology, you know, a settlement or a town when the major stuff starts
is happening is
going to come a little later in starting in really the 19th century BC.
Okay. So in the 19th century BC, this group of tribes comes in from the East.
Okay. And so this is another thing about Mesopotamian history.
Mesopotamia doesn't have good natural borders.
subject to a lot of invasion. So they get invaded a lot. Yeah. Right. They get
invaded by... and it's not just, oh, some other empire that's their neighbor builds
up a bigger army and then comes and invades. It's like barbarians coming and
sacking cities and stuff all the time. Right. Right. They come down out of the
mountains and... Because there aren't good, defensible natural borders. And this
This is true also for...
So this group comes from out of Syria into Mesopotamia. So they come from the west
and Syria the 19th century BC they move in and they capture a bunch of cities including Babylon
and so they get called by the Acadians the Amurru which means westerner, guy from the west
Okay.
Good.
And...
Amuru is where the biblical amurites comes from.
Yeah, I remember them.
Yes.
So an amurite is used, including in the Torah, but even after the Torah into Joshua's,
Amorite is used as a catch-all often for giant clans.
Yeah, right. And, you know, the famous...
King Sion of the Amorites whose defeat is commemorated in Psalms.
Yeah, alongside Og King of the Refine.
But when they're referred to together, like In Joshua, they're referred to as the Amorite Kings.
So Og even gets lumped in there because again, it's used as sort of a catch-all for giant clans.
So the most famous one of these amurites particularly in Babylon is Hammurabi.
or hemorapi if you're a hipster.
Um, the hemorapi's code guy.
Yeah, that, yeah.
So I think he shows up in civilization.
I think you can play him.
I think he's the king of Babylon and so, and so yeah.
Right.
So his, I don't want to digress on this too much, but, uh,
his law code is technically not a law code.
Oh man, thank you.
The disappointment.
Um, but he does propagate laws, right?
Right.
And he propagates the...
laws on publicly visible standing stones that we still have. So that's why we know so much about
Howard Robbie's so-called code in the airquence. But so, Hammer Robbie establishes not only builds up
Babylon into a city, but he makes it into the capital city of an empire. And this is really the first
stem
empire. Right? This is the original empire because you had, you know, as we mentioned, a
cod and sumer going back and forth, right? But like, these are neighbors in Mesopotamia.
Yeah. Just a local thing. And there are tribal movements and shifts at
population shifts and stuff. But when we talk about an empire, when we talk about a trans
national empire that has like trade and infrastructure.
and is able to move things from literally one side of the known world to the other.
Right? The first one of those is Hamarabi's Babylonian Empire.
And he ended up conquering like all the Mesopotamian cities you've heard of.
So Ur-Uruk, Eridu, that we talked about last time. Right?
Hold on to other ones, they're less common.
known he took, but his reach extended, he went up into Asia Minor, he went and his reach
with trade, here's how extensive it was, you know, we call this the Bronze Age, right?
Right. He was getting his bronze by going to Cyprus to get copper, right? That's where Cyprus
gets its name. In fact the word Cypress and copper are Cognate. Yes. Yes.
that's literally where it goes today.
The go to Cyprus ticket copper and then mind 10 in what's now Afghanistan.
Yeah, because you have to have both and bring it back and smelt it.
Right.
Indebrans.
Hamarabi also we know really liked the style of sandals they made in Crete.
So he would get them imported.
Those pre-sandals.
The sandals.
Yes.
Those were the hot sandals.
Yes, he was the speaker head of his day.
But so that shows you that shows you here in the, you know, first half of the second millennium
BC, right, that this empire connected the world, right?
This is this is the first world empire and brought what was at the time these wonders of
technology.
Right, and this cosmopolitan trade, right, and in the sort of imperial propaganda, this
was because the Amuru, the Emirates had brought back the Golden Age from before the flood.
Yeah, this idea of anti-deluvian knowledge.
they had through their connection with the gun.
Right? Maintained this secret wisdom from the Opcala we've talked about, right? The Opcala
stories of Babylonian story, right? Of this knowledge that was revealed to the kings before
the flood and now the Amorites have it, right? And that is what has allowed them to establish,
to establish this great empire.
So this is, and this is so...
thorough that, you know, we talked to several times already now about Akkad and Sumer,
right? It's being these two Mesopotamian regions and Mesopotamian powers that go back and forth.
You don't hear about either of them in the Old Testament, right? Like, I mean, you hear about cities,
right? Like Orr, right? But the word Sumer or Sumerian or the word Akkadian, or Akkad don't show up.
Yeah, right. But that's because
of how successful this empire is at transforming even how people view the world.
So before this you have a cod and summa or Sumeria, right? After this the
northern region of Mesopotamia is called Assyria and the southern portion is
called Babylonia. And so that's why when we get into the former prophets what are
sometimes called the historical books of the Old Testament.
it. You see these references to Assyria and Babylonia, right? Babylon. And you don't see references
to Sumer and Akat because Babylon, this first great world empire, sort of looms large, right?
And of course, it doesn't still exist. So it collapses. When people based on the Old Testament,
think about the Babylonian Empire you're thinking about.
like Nebuchadnezzar and his father Nabopalacir, right? That's called the Neo-Babalonean Empire.
Yeah. They were self consciously trying to reconstruct, after they defeated the Assyrians,
they were trying to self consciously reconstruct and appropriate homerobs original Babylonian empire.
From like what a thousand years before? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. A little more than a thousand years before. Yeah.
Yeah.
like the Holy Roman Empire. You know. Right? Come on man. None of those words were correct. You're not
fooling anybody. But so this original Empire collapses, it's collapse is really the beginning. It
sets the balls rolling that ultimately produce the Bronze Age collapse, the collapse of the Bronze Age
as such.
Right. So it starts with barbarians from the edges, right?
Coming and starting to sack cities. Babylon itself got sacked, I believe, 1499 for the first time.
This is all going to repeat with the Roman Empire, right?
Later on, the Western Roman Empire, right.
So it starts getting sacked, things start to crumble, right?
And then when you...
get as you move into the second half of the second millennium BC,
everything just falls apart.
That's all of these trade relationships fall apart.
It's not that people like forgot how to smelt bronze.
It's just that they couldn't get copper in tin,
logistically.
And so it collapses the beginning of everything's collapse.
Right, and so...
The whole period, so the Exodus is portrayed as happening during this period where Egypt actually
survives the Bronze Age collapse, which is massively weakened. And when we get, this is part of
the background when we get into judges and first Samuel and second Samuel, or first and second
kingdoms in the Orthodox study Bible. Right? What that part of history...
is literally post-apocalyptic.
Hmm.
Huh.
Right, like they are in the ruins
of this broad-stage civilization.
So basically judges is sort of the Mad Max of his era.
Yes, yes.
Yeah.
Wow.
And yeah.
And then first and second Samuels,
like the last 30 or so issues of walking dead,
right, where they're pulling civilization back together.
right and that's so we tend to have this very medieval western read of King
Saul and King David partially due to Renaissance art but in actuality
especially Saul was basically a tribal chief 10 and David was maybe a step
above that right they were really pulling things again I mean you'll read these
things like
At the time Saul becomes king, like the Philistines have basically made sure that there weren't any blacksmiths.
Israelite blacksmiths. So they don't even have like weapons.
Wow.
They're fighting with like farm implements.
Right? They don't have a standing army.
So yeah, so there's this apocalypse that happens. The broads age collapse.
and those earliest stories.
are crawling out of sort of that wreckage.
The Philistines themselves were one of the sea peoples
who came from the Greek islands
because of climate change and economic collapse in famine.
They migrated south, they tried to invade Egypt and lost.
And so they settled along the coast of the Levant.
That's why you have those coastal Philistines cities.
Right.
So there
remnants of this collapse, right?
This like apocalypse.
Yeah, and so that's why it's such a big deal in, in first Samuel, when Goliath comes out,
because not only is he a giant, right, but he's wearing all bronze.
Yeah, he's this warrior of the ancient days.
Yeah, he's got a magical item in every slot, basically, because they couldn't make any of those,
they don't have enough bronze to make any. That's why
It goes on and on about the weight of these things.
Like no one has that much bronze to make something like that,
even if they wanted to at this point.
So yeah, so there's this collapse that happens
of that empire centered around the city of Babylon.
And then from the whole world having been sort of pulled together
by that empire and connected
by that empire, everything ends up fragmented and confused. So as a last note, this is a pattern
that will be familiar to our longtime listeners. At Babylon during this period, the main gods who are
being worshipped are Shemesh, who's the Sun God, the Semitic Sun God, that Samson's parents name
after as the sort of most high God and then
and Marduk at this point has seen as his son,
sort of besides in the Council of the Gods,
sort of like hell and bail or Krona's in suicide.
Yeah, exactly.
The same pattern is going on there.
And just like in those other cases,
Shemesh sort of drifts off
and Marduk sort of becomes the main show.
Yeah, we'll talk about this pattern
a little bit more on our next episode.
But our fourth coming.
Yes.
Thunder Gods.
Oh, oh wait, rock.
So with that in mind, right, about Babylon, right, and what Babylon would have represented
in the sort of common imaginary of the people at the time that the Torah is first being
promulgated, it's first being heard.
Now we can go back to Genesis 11 and sort of set the telling of the story there over
against this background.
So one of the things we see right off the bat is this idea that everyone speaks the same
language.
Yeah, yeah, this is where you break.
It's not quite Sunday school for me, but you're breaking something for me.
But go ahead, break it.
It's fine.
You know that this is very very very
personal for me. Yes, the idea here is is, I guess this is not meant as sort of a literal thing.
Right. It's a knife to the heart man, but they're not actually all speaking the same language.
The idea is this is a way of portraying an interconnected world. Right. They're all on the same
page. This is speaking the same language like when someone comes up to me as a Dutchman and offers
me a coupon, I say, now you're speaking my language.
It's in that sense.
Would you like a discount, sir?
So the idea is that all of humanity is united.
And what's it united by?
By this city of this tower, right?
By Babylon.
Yeah, so the idea of a single language is symbolic.
Right.
It's pulled them together to this common purpose, right?
So then if we back up a little bit.
into chapter 10, right? Another one of these little interjections happens in the genealogy of Ham.
And that is about this Nimrod fellow.
Oh yeah, Nimrod. Wait, Hunter. Yes, well, and for our millennial and zoomer listeners,
There was a time.
way back in the long ago when calling someone a Nimrod was a great insult.
That's true. That kind of an idiot sort of. Yeah.
And I have no idea how exactly that happened. Right. Because there's nothing in the text that
suggests you as some kind of stupid person. But that was a thing at one point.
There you are. In the ancient world of the 1970s.
Thanks.
Um.
So, what we read about Nimrod in Genesis 10, 8, 9, is that he's the son of Kush and he's the first on earth to be a mighty man.
Yeah, what's the Hebrew word there for mighty man?
Good boy.
Right, which should remind us all Genesis chapter 6.
six. Yes, that's the same. These were the mighty man of old, right?
The man of her noun.
Right, so he's a mighty a mighty hunter before the Lord before it is said like Nimrod a mighty hunter before the Lord
So it's gonna be the origin of a saying so Nimrod
Is not only connected to the giants by that Genesis 6 4 reference
but
Also by the fact of his name which is linguistically
identical to
Okay, so...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, Mr. Tamion. Yeah, so he's literally hearing the same name as this God. Right, right. So
What this text this genealogy is doing is saying is identifying this mess of the Tamion God as actually being
this giant figure
Right, never so if you've been reading Genesis for a few chapters by this point you would say to yourself
We have seen this before.
Yeah.
Dianne's
Are rising again?
Yes.
So we have this pattern, right?
What was the pattern?
Genesis, you know, four through nine, we have the genealogy of
cane and that leads us up to and rolls us like we talked about last time,
rolls us into the flood, where everything gets destroyed.
Right.
Death by holiness happens to purify, to purify the earth.
And so if we're reading along here we should see oh
Oh boy, right. It's all starting to happen again. The same cycle is repeating. We have this genealogy.
We have giants showing up, right. Everything is repeating, right. And so the biblical story,
then, by that pattern, fundamentally agrees with the Babylonian propaganda about it, right?
because the Babylonian propaganda was yes we are
the new incarnation of before the flood. Right? So the text of Genesis is very much
saying yes, they were the new incarnation of what was before the flood. And that's bad.
Right? This is terrible. Right? And so we have this element, sort of the central element here,
the sort of this purpose, what are they trying to do?
Yeah, right. This isn't, this isn't the beginning of Genesis 11 where it says,
in verse four, they said, come, let us build ourselves a city and a tower with its top in the heavens,
and let us make a name for ourselves, let's we be dispersed over the face of the whole earth.
Right. And so they're trying to build, right, this tower up to heaven, right.
Yeah, that is.
is in part going to sort of cement this union of humanity, right, in this empire.
Now, this may be a ruin Sunday school also. Now they think about it. So, sort of like when
the snake lost his legs, people read this as like, oh, those dummies, they thought they
could just build a really tall tower and it would reach God up and heaven, right?
because of course they knew that God's existed at a certain altitude.
Right.
I mean, that's...
It's where you have to think that's what they think.
But allow me to suggest,
if that's what they were really trying to do,
God wouldn't have had to do anything.
Yeah, right.
He wouldn't have needed to stop them.
He could just let them go.
But like, okay guys, have fun, right?
So there's no reason to sort of punish that.
It's its own punishment, because it's stupid, right?
But this is something which God feels the need.
to put an end to.
So if we look at how this idea of someone wanting
to ascend into heaven, someone wanting
to ascend to the heavens.
And this is part of how we know we're talking about a ziggurat,
because the word ziggurat literally means like a high or raised
place.
OK.
But we look at how that that place.
out in the rest of Scripture. So Deuteronomy 30 verse 12, talking about the
commandments of the Torah and obeying them, says it is not in heaven that you
should say who will ascend to heaven for us and bring it to us that we may
hear it and do it. So the idea here is that this reaching up to heaven is to go
up there and bring it up.
something down, not to go up there and live up there. Right. Right. So this isn't,
people isn't man seeking some alternate way of salvation. Right. Like salvation is going
to heaven and we're going to get there by building a tower. Right. That's not how this works.
Right. It's to bring something down. And then Saint Paul
applies this idea even further in Romans 10 verse 6
where he says with the
righteousness based on faithfulness,
I'll really translate it,
says, do not say in your heart who will ascend into heaven,
right, so he's referencing Deuteronomy.
It says that is to bring Christ down.
Yeah, so it's again, it's this image of going up there
to bring something down, right.
And so someone may say, well, how do you know
that what St. Paul's talking about in Romans
is what's going on here?
Well, let's say passes and...
makes no sense if he's not talking about what's going on here. Right? Why would who will go up for us into heaven mean bring Christ down from heaven?
Right. Like there's no frame within which that makes sense. Like no one ever... Right. Yeah. Not other than this. Right. Right. Exactly. Right.
Right, so the idea here, the problem, the problem is not that they think they could build something tall enough to reach heaven.
The
The problem is that they're trying to bring God down.
Yeah, and this is exactly how idolatry works in the ancient world.
Set up an idol, bring a God into it, make it do what you want.
Right.
And then that, and they're doing that so that, right, to sort of empower and preserve their empire.
They want to bring God down to elevate themselves, not literally elevate themselves, right?
but in order to preserve.
right this empire so in the story Yahweh does come down
But he went when God comes for a visit right? It's not get out the the tea and biscuits right it's
Things are gonna get settled right so
You might think well if God comes down into this scene these people are all gonna get wiped out
Right they're just gonna get obliterated right like
Bye.
going to be like Sodom and Gomorrah. But we just had a story that preceded this about the flood.
Right. And that's what happened in the story about the flood. So the first time this pattern happened,
yes, everyone got destroyed. But then afterwards, God made a promise.
Right. And he sat down his bow in the clouds. And again, rainbows not bow like a pretty bow on a
present. It's bow like a bow and arrow.
God sets it down in the clouds.
And that's a sign because every time you see it,
you can say, yeah, it's still sitting there.
He hasn't picked it back up again.
That's the idea.
Yeah.
Right.
And so he's not going to destroy humanity again.
He's laid down his arms.
Right.
But so if humanity has become wicked like they did before the flood.
And if God has promised not to wipe them all out again,
what's the other
option besides death by holiness.
God has to separate himself from humanity.
So rather than them being able to sort of pull God down and make him do what they wanted,
instead he pulls back and disperses them.
So this is Genesis depicting the bronjee's collapse.
as being an act of God, and it's bound up in this story of the city and the tower of Babylon
here at the beginning of Genesis, chapter 11. Right. That that previous civilization was just
as wicked. It was the reproduction of the one before the flood that was also wicked. And so God is the
the one who brought that down.
And as we're going to talk about here in a little bit,
in the second half established a new order, a new world order.
That's after this assembly of the Bronze Age civilization.
But before we get to that, here at the end of the first half of three,
just a couple of notes. Right. The first big note being about
We've been going through Genesis one.
through 11 basically these last three shows, three episodes.
And that's appropriate because we're talking about the three false of man
that are recorded there.
There is sort of a shift in the way the narrative is told at this point in
Genesis in the sense that starting with chapter 12 with Abraham were
reading about the life of a guy, his son, his grandson,
and his great grandsons.
And it's sort of the narrative is going through
the lives of these people,
whereas the first 11 chapters are a little more
of a macro view in the sense that we don't like
follow Enoch or Cain or Seth,
like even Adam and Eve,
their lives like...
over the course of their lives. Right. We find out about their deaths like in a genealogy. Right.
We don't read a narrative account of their life in their death. Right. So there is a,
there are differences there. Okay. But it has become very common
in scholarly circles and non scholarly circles, even some orthodox circles,
to talk about this massive genre difference, I mean Genesis 1 through 11 and
Genesis 12 through 50. These are really two like they're all lumped together
into the book of Genesis but these are really two doing two completely different
things. Yeah, that the beginning is quote-unquote myth and then the rest is
his quote-unquote history.
as though the history part you're supposed to take this pretty literally but the
stuff before that is all kind of big sweeping symbols and who stories of the
ancient world yeah yeah that's the technical term for methodological studies
by the way yeah well you have to draw it out like three or four syllables well
they just sound like you're doing a ghost impression well ghosts are related
all of this. Or you could do Herkyloid. It's like
And so, yeah.
And so then the first 11 chapters, right,
we just sort of set aside in terms of anything
to do with history and try to extract something from it,
whether it's some kind of moral lessons,
whether it's some kind of, I mean, lately,
Not good.
temporary world. It's basically like the only reason Adam and Evert in the Bible is to tell us what manhood and womanhood are right that's it
Right and can't enable you can't get much out of except you know murdering your brother is bad
skip all the genealogies
flood bad
Tell our people don't talk much about it all don't really know what to do with it
Yeah, and so there's
There's a lot of problems with this.
One of the biggest ones is that
ancient people may know such distinction
between myth and history.
Yeah, it's not a thing.
Medieval people didn't even make a distinction
between myth and history.
Right, a little.
No. No.
It doesn't stop at late antiquity.
Yeah, like for instance,
you know, in our next episode,
we're gonna talk about very briefly,
I'm gonna mention saxochromaticus,
Danish.
historian from the 12th century and he does a whole book of the you know the origins of the kings of Norway
right of sorry of well the Danish kings and so forth and he starts with what we would consider to be prehistory
and then shows how they're kind of descended from those that our worship does gods up there
you know on up to his own point in history yeah like it's all just one big narrative for him yeah and so nobody I mean
you look
the genealogies of Christ and the New Testament, right? They don't indicate like, okay, well,
this Adam guy, you know, sat there, you know, then you get to Abraham, you're like, okay, now we're
in, now we're in history territory. Right. Like, there was not mythos just means story.
Historia also means kind of story of a people, right? These are really the same thing,
right in the ancient world. And so
Part of the what causes this problem for modern people is modernism, right? That's why they have a problem
reading Genesis 1 through 11, right? The same way they read 12 through 50. Because of existing
pre-suppositions that we already have.
Right?
If you just come to it fresh with no knowledge of...
anything you would not have any reason to read to suddenly make this jump at
chapter 11. And allow me to suggest that if what we've said so far on this show
is correct, right, you'd really have to split it at chapter 9. Right? Because
chapter 11 is basically just talking about history the same way like the
books of the Kingswell, if what we're saying.
Here is correct. So now you've got to move it back to chapter 9. And you can make a better,
you can make a better argument for that. You could say, well, see before the flood, this is a
different age, right? Sort of this view of ages. There's like paradise as an age
before the flood is an age from the flood to, um, to Christ as an age, right? You could try that.
Maybe just move it back to nine. This maybe I'll turn this into my
another version of my conversation with
like why don't you just use 135 AD, it works better, right?
But 70, anyway.
You just say here, maybe divided it at 9, but nobody does that, right?
They include the tariff label.
But so if you approach, not just Genesis 1 through 11,
the scriptures in general, with a definition of truth that's based in modernism,
modern materialism specifically, then your definition of truth is what is true
is what corresponds to material reality.
And so if I had a time machine and a video camera,
or my phone and somehow magically my cell phone worked
in the exit past without towers,
and not being able to recharge it,
and I recorded something,
that happened, that this is what I would see.
What is written here on this page is exactly what I would see.
what I would see, right? If I went back...
and did that. That's our modern sort of, to us, they didn't have a concept of time travel and they didn't have a concept of
recording devices in the ancient world. So when we criticize this sometimes,
I think and I think this because of comments we get when we criticize this. I think some of our listeners
hear us saying when we say this that we somehow don't believe that these things
really happen.
or we're saying that the writers of Scripture didn't know or didn't care whether these things really happened.
Yeah, really happened, quote unquote.
Right, quote unquote really happened.
Right. And just that phrase really happened.
You're already in this idea of corresponds to material reality.
But I have no doubt that if you did have a turning.
and you went back and you talked to one of the writers of Scripture. It would take you a while to explain your question
frankly
Right. Yeah, like when you said to them. So are these the exact words Moses said maybe like
Yeah, I said that's what Moses said no, no, we're those the exact words
But once you explained it to them what you meant by the question. I'm pretty sure every one of the biblical writers would say yes
Right, let's say yes.
This is what really happened. Yes, this is what actually happened. But that's not what's in their mind as they were writing it.
Yeah. That's not how they thought about history. Right. And thought about the world. And it's not how they define truth. Right. Because they didn't have the concept of time trial. They didn't have the right.
They knew that if you asked eye witnesses to something
To describe what happened and what people
said they wouldn't 100% agree, right? And so they understood this and they understood that that didn't mean the event didn't happen.
Yeah, people had different perspectives and they were able to hear different parts and see different parts and we're looking from different angle, right? They were actually very sophisticated understanding that.
that. But so that's and that's only one definition of truth. That's not the only definition
of truth.
right? That's not the only definition of truth that we use every day, right? So another common
modern definition of truth is basically a utilitarian one, right? What's true is what works.
Right? So if I come to you or let's say Shakyu-Lonil comes to you to sell you Goldbond Medicated Cream
And he tells you, rub this on your knee and it'll help you with your dry knee.
Right? So you get some and you rub it on your knee, right?
If it works, if your knee is less crusty than X-ray, right?
Then you will say, yes, what Shaq told me is the true, right?
And that was not in the notes.
Yes.
Most of what I say is not in the notes.
Well, that's usually related to the notes in some way.
I wasn't expecting Shikilu, Neil and Goldbomb.
He's everywhere man. He's like it is commercial. He's got you general car insurance gold
bodman anyway. Yes. Good for you, Shaq. Good for you. Get your money. But that kind of utilitarian
definition, right? Again, that we use all the time. Right? There's some something is either
true or false based on whether it actually works. Right? Whether it actually does what it says on the
the 10, right?
There's also various philosophical definitions of truth.
We might say something is true because it expresses some first principle or gives us
some insight into human behavior or the way society works or the way the world works.
We use this all the time when we talk about, we read a work that we know is fiction.
we say, hey, something this novel said is really
true. Right? When we say that, we're not claiming that it's not fiction. Right. Right.
We're claiming that it said something to or this film or whatever said something true in the
sense that it provided some insight. Right. Into the way things work. But we're not saying, yes,
the events depicted in this film are what really happened at some point to some person. Right.
the following is based on a true
And based on it, they're both in English.
So all of these examples, right, and we could give more examples of different ways that we think of truth, something being true.
Right. All of these are really grounded in different definitions of reality.
Right. So again, that idea of corresponding to material reality is based on being a materialist.
being a materialist.
right? What's real is what's material is what what that's only only only the material is real and everything else is
Something else and what could be experienced with the senses, right?
So if I had the time machine. This is what I would see happening. Yeah
And you know some of those philosophical definitions, right? If you ask Plato
Or somebody suffering from Plato brain, right?
what truth is, it's not going to be any...
Anything you can see with your senses, anything you can experience with your senses is not
really going to be true.
Right.
What's going to be true is going to be the first principles that underlie maybe very far
removed from the things you experience with your senses.
Yeah.
All this is just kind of an illusion of sorts.
Right.
Well, it's a shadow of an image of an actual thing.
Yeah.
And so, right, they're in these different definitions of reality, but these are things we can navigate,
because we use these different definitions in different circumstances. If you come to me and say,
hey, Father Steven, your house is on fire, right? My concern is going to be that this is true
in a modern materialist sense, right?
Because, hey, what do you mean by?
fire. Yes. Or we're not going to sit and be like, you know, to quote what will
no doubt go down in history is one of the greatest films of all time. You'd run into a burning
building to save someone you don't even know, but your marriage is burning down all around you.
Wow. You just referenced fire proof. I did. I just quote it. Wow. Wow. This may be our first
Kurt's here.
reference in the entire podcast everybody. Right. Like I'm not going to be thinking that that's not
where I'm going to go with it. Right. Are you talking about my marriage? Have I not been caring
for my wife adequately? Right. I'm going to drive to my house and see if it is odd fire.
Like literally burning down. That's going to be my immediate concern. Right. There's not
something wrong with that that doesn't make me a materialist. Right. In fact, that that's going to be my
my first in...
interpretation. So what all this means, the reason I'm rambling and ranting about all this
and quoting Kirk Cameron, that actually wasn't Kirk Cameron, that was Kirk Cameron's friend,
that's what he said to him. Oh right snap him out of his dogmatic slumber.
All of this is aimed at, so if we're going to talk about the book of Genesis or any other part of
of the scriptures.
We need to, the question we need to ask is, how is Genesis looking at reality?
How is it defining truth?
Yeah, yeah.
Genesis is not simply giving a list of objective facts.
And that we should understand that it's not actually an introduction to the whole story
of Babylon.
It's a response to an existing story that the first listeners and readers would have already
no
like they would have known, oh, they're talking about Babylon. Let's hear this take on it. And it's,
and this is the Bible's correction and commentary on what's going on with Babylon, with the collapse of that empire,
and how that is, is to be understood by the people of God. This is what God is saying about this.
Right. Just like when Genesis 6 starts talking about a flood,
None of the original hairs would have been-
like, oh, there was a flood. Right. Everybody knew there was a flood. Everybody knew it wiped
out a previous civilization. Right. So everybody knew Babylon had been founded and everybody knew
the Babylonian empire had collapsed and everybody knew that that was the first and the string of
dominos that led to worldwide civilization collapsing. Right. They all knew that. Yeah. Right. So
this is giving a perspective on it. Right. This is giving a perspective on it of what was actually
happening.
frankly apocalyptic in the sense that we've used it before on the show, in the
sense that it's revealing the spiritual reality behind those historical events.
Right. And this is part of why it doesn't, Genesis 11 doesn't feel the need to
give us a date. Yeah. Right. It doesn't feel the need to give us a ton of
geographic locators.
short little text just assumes you all we all know what's being talked about right right right
and we see how it's being characterized yeah but so um Babylon isn't just here in Genesis at the
beginning of the Bible as sort of the first empire but Babylon is seen as sort of the the principal
behind all world empires.
And we could not only see this along the way through the
But we even see this if we go from Genesis all the way to the end to Revelation, right?
And even near the end of Revelation
There's sort of an ominous and Revelation 16 verse 19. There's sort of this ominous statement where God remembers Babylon
Right, and this isn't like oh God it's forgotten about it, right?
But this is like now he's it's time for another visit
Okay
And so then in
After 17 and 18, we have this whole depiction.
This is the horror of Babylon that's referred to who sits on seven hills like Rome, right?
Wait, what?
Because Rome was the current Babylon.
Yeah.
Right.
Babylon, the type.
represents this two, references this two.
But so, this is true for revelation in general.
So, you know, St. John says in 1 John,
you have heard that an antichrist will come
and already antichrist plural or at large in the world.
So, the same thing is true with Babylon.
Yes, there will be a last world empire.
But
There's already been a first and there's a whole bunch in between.
And they're all Babylon because they're all founded on that same spirit.
Yeah, they're all founded on this idea of uniting humanity humanity,
uniting itself.
Toward a common person's purpose, which is its own glory.
And trying to drag God down and put him in service of it.
So here's
my attempt at cancellation number 352 the current one is the United States of America.
There we are. I might be canceled already. I'm not canceling you but
up until World War II was the British Empire. Yeah. I mean the reality is we are the
we are the current world empire that's pulling the most strings and you know put yeah. I don't
think it's gonna last much longer if that makes anybody feel you better but I can't
Give me your honor.
What was your feeling?
Yeah, who knows what happens next, right?
All right, well, the Brits have already experienced
the end of that.
Yeah.
But yeah, United the World Through Trade, et cetera,
et cetera, et cetera.
Yeah.
So this is, but the key here,
the key here is that I'm not saying the United States
is the last one.
I'm not saying it's the ultimate one.
I'm not saying, and this is part of the problem.
like people who read Revelation and Daniel not so well want to play pin the tail on the
Antichrist, right? They want to play pin the tail on one world government, right? So they
almost never picked the United States though. They usually pick the EU, right? And frankly,
I don't know if the EU could run a successful like toothbrush distribution campaign, let
will let establish a new world order at this point.
But...
Okay. But that pin the tail on the new world order is not new either. Right. Yeah. It was Napoleon.
Right. It was Hitler. It was Stalin. It was, I mean, right. All of these, right. Evil empires.
Yeah. The past have all been right. V1, right. And none of them yet are the one. Eventually,
there will be a last one.
But the point is, and the point here is not to rag on the United States of America, but
to point to what happened after World War II with the ascendancy of the United States
economy is that we entered into that imperial position.
And so there will always be that temptation, right, for this empire, just like all the other
other ones to try to you.
and I humanity around its own glory to try to sort of demote God to being underneath it
and use God for its purposes to justify what it's going to do.
And so this is something, I mean, I mean, Rome was doing this while the Apostles were
alive, at least a couple of them like St. Paul were Roman citizens, right?
Yeah.
This doesn't be they were evil, right?
Does it mean St Paul stopped praying for the emperor because he's...
decided the whole, you know, Roman Empire was satanic, right?
He wanted to, right, convert the Emperor to Christianity,
and that ultimately happened with St. Constantine,
and the Empire was changed, and it crumbled.
Bad news, for everybody who doesn't realize
the Byzantine Empire fell.
And it's interesting that one of the marks
of St. Constantine and St. P. Adosius is Christianizing
I'm sorry.
of the empire was that after that, neither in the West or the East, did the empire actually
function as a world empire. They weren't actively going out and conquering and consuming,
right? The kind of things that were said about the Roman Empire before that, right? They've
created a wasteland and called it peace. Doesn't really work once you get to the Christian
in emperors.
I think that may have been why it's days were numbered.
There you go.
It was no longer playing by the world's rules.
And, you know,
yep, yep.
All right.
People still wear.
Well, all that said,
we can go ahead and go to our first break.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment.
To take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
give them a call at 855-237-2-
That's 855-A-F-Radio.
For all of us, male or female, parent or not, that's what it's often like, isn't it?
It's at the end of our own tether that the miracle happens.
It is in our greatest weakness that God strength is known.
when we decrease that he can increase.
it's in losing our life that we find it.
To put it another way, it's in the spot where St. Morena falls down, exhausted that her spring
rises up.
It's when the people of God curse Moses in the wilderness and wish themselves back in Egypt
that they hear the crack of the staff, the gush of water through the rock.
It's when God himself is spat upon and mocked and bleeding and dead that the glorious
resurrection is ushered in.
From seven holy women, conversations with saints and friends, now available as an audio
book at Audible, Amazon and iTunes.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everybody. It's the second part.
of our show, we're talking about the Tower of Babel. And we just, I think there's one of our
longer first halves, about 90 minutes there. We just went through the whole context of the building
of the city and Tower of Babelon. Again, Babel equals Babelon in Scripture. So now we're going to
kind of shift gears a little bit. And we do have a caller waiting, but I think we're going to hold
hold on to that call until the point in this half where what she's asking about makes the
most sense.
So just hold on, Collar, we hear you.
We know you're sick.
I think I'm supposed to mention I have a new book out,
but here's the thing.
Oh, yes, you do have a notebook.
I don't want to say the name.
Because that way this podcast will age better.
Does that kind of always have a new book out?
I hope that's always going to be the case, Father.
So right, if we don't say the name six months from now,
somebody listening, this will be like,
oh, Father, see if it has a new book out.
And then just whatever it is, whatever it is,
I'll go get it.
Here we go.
And what is new when we're talking about cosmic time anyway?
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
So the writing of books, there is no end.
That's crazy asses.
Yes.
Yep.
All right.
So something happens after this event,
after the people event, as it were, right?
What's going on in connection with that?
Well, so this attempt to restore the antediluvian
ordering of the world gets ended, right? And something else is given to replace it, right?
So the resulting state of affairs is also seen by the Torah to be the product of God's action. Right?
So, we see this laid out in large parts.
actually in Deuteronomy chapter 32. I know there are some folks out there who get excited
just mentioning that chapter. Which is one of the oldest parts of the Torah. And you know what's
funny is that's actually me saying that is probably more likely to get me canceled than
saying that the US is an empire because there's somebody out there going Moses wrote all of it
at the same time. Right.
When I say it's the oldest, right, again, the Hebrew, that the oldest versions of the Torah that we have today is written in, did not exist at the time Moses lived, right?
So things have been updated, things have been translated, right? It's in a different alphabet, right, et cetera, et cetera.
So when I say this is one of the oldest portions, I mean, Deuteronomy 32, the other big one is Exodus chapter 15, the song of the sea.
Hmm.
These are the parts of the Torah in Hebrew that show the least sign of editing.
So they're in a very antiquated form of Hebrew that's frankly very hard to translate.
Yeah, because there's almost nothing else like it out there.
Yeah. There's a lot of words that are only used here.
One of the verses we're going to about to quote has a word that's only used here.
used here that's a Babylonian loan word. Right?
It's not even a Hebrew word.
So yeah, so that's what I mean by oldest part meaning oldest in the sense that it's still in sort of its original form, right?
It has a bit edited or updated or smoothed out the way some other sections have yeah into later Hebrew
So
This starts in Deuteronomy 32 verse a which we've coded a bunch
on the show. Yep, yep. So when the Most High gave to the nations there in
Heritans when he divided mankind he fixed the borders of the peoples according
to the number of the sons of God. And that's the from the Hebrew version in the
Greek Old Testament, it's according to the number of his angels. Yeah. Now that's the
according to the Dead Sea Scrolls Hebrew. Oh yeah, the sons of God reading. What you find in the
later Maseritic texts as they've edited sons of God.
to the suns of Israel.
Which makes no sense because Israel doesn't even exist at this time.
Yeah, so people just thought the Greek was weird.
Well, that would have been the suns of Israel in the sense of,
like Israel, like Jacob.
Oh, okay.
Which would give you 12.
And then you get some people who do the special pleading of like,
well, there's like 70 or 72 people who go down into Egypt at the end of the day.
Wow.
Thank you.
I mean, this is, you know, there is a reference to the number of the peoples in Genesis 10.
Yeah, you got the table of nations and Israel's not there.
So you got to ignore, yeah, you got to ignore Genesis 10.
You got to ignore how like all the church fathers at all of Second Temple Jews.
Jewish literature reads this and you got to say that the Greek translation got it wrong.
Yeah, so.
But if you really want to defend the Hebrew text from 1000 AD as being, no, this is the
right one.
You know, have fun with that.
I have no interest in doing it.
Right, but so this is the most high God, right?
Yahweh gives to when he divides mankind, right?
A tarot of Bable, fix their borders,
according to the numbers of the sons of God,
which there were 70 or 72.
And as you mentioned in Genesis 10,
we have sort of the table of nations.
And there are...
70 nations. So this is a side note. This is me grinding an axe slash beating a dead horse.
But one of the worst things about English Bibles, mostly English New Testaments is the
the fact that they use the word Gentiles.
Okay, which is a Latin word, right?
For what?
So there's no reason to use it.
And they're using that to translate the word nations.
Yeah.
And inconsistently.
Right.
Because sometimes they will translate it as nations.
But it both gives this sort of ethnic thing of Jews and Gentiles.
Like this is an ethnic issue of peoples.
Yeah.
Right.
But what that's translating is the phrase nations.
reference to like the most accurate
translation of that would be pretty much every time you see Gentiles would be to have the 70 nations.
Yeah, I mean it's weird because like Gentile in its oldest form simply does mean nations.
Like it's related to the word, you know, the word, GENS, GENS, which means a kind, you know, but I think
I think in the medieval period it comes to mean non-Jews. Yeah, yeah. Well, it's weird. Yeah, in English,
in English I mean.
Yeah, yeah, oh yeah.
Yeah, yeah, because like I mean Thomas Aquinas uses that word to mean
Muslims, oh, yeah, that's fun. Yeah, but that's all
But my point being this idea of the 70 nations is what lies behind that yeah
Right, it's these 70 nations that were divided right
And are out there
And no, I know, I know some of...
you out there who still have the spreadsheet in your head are thinking, well wait a minute,
are there still only 70? Do they drop out and like new ones with a new nation form that
we're not talking about nation states, right? We're not, this is symbolic number, right?
The idea here is that you have the 70 nations and then you have Israel, which is not a nation
in which God creates for himself, right? But the purpose
of the creation of Israel as this separate nation is through that nation to save the 70 nations
So yeah, this is that's a very literal reference to the nations right that means right the peoples of the world
so then in
That's what we're talking about.
happens at the Tower of Babel, then in Deuteronomy 32-17, we see that things
didn't sort of go as planned. Right. Or did go the way they should have.
Yeah. We've been better. So you get they sacrifice to demons that were no
gods to gods they had never known to new gods that had come recently, whom
your fathers had never dreaded. And we should probably say where it says to
demons that were no gods to gods they had never known. If you
the first part of saying these demons weren't really gods and then it seems like it's talking about
two different groups of beings like to demons and then to gods that they had never known. But the
point in saying that they were no gods remember and we talked about this I think are very first
couple of episodes that that gods in almost every ancient language has this sense of being rulers.
They were ruling right so the point is is that these demons are not really the rulers. You know
that God is the ruler, so they're not...
that, but then the verse proceeds to use that exact same word because that's the shorthand
word to refer to spirits.
Yeah.
And the word that translated demons there in Hebrew is Shedium, which is putting a Hebrew
plural ending on Shedu, which is a Babylonian word for a territorial spirit, being a spirit
that's the spirit of a particular region or place or geographical feature.
Yeah.
Right. So they were not supposed to start worshiping the spirits of these places once they got to these places. Right. It's the idea.
But that's not sort of the end of the story right here at Deuteronomy 32 because when we get to verse 43, there's this promise of this reckoning. Yeah. Okay. So this one says, rejoice with him, O heavens.
bow down to him all gods, for he avenges the blood of his children.
and takes vengeance on his adversaries, he repays those who hate him and cleanses his people's land.
So, bow down to him all gods.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So, this is sort of, so within the movement of Deuteronomy 32,
right, you have the dispersal of the people's and of the nations, right?
So this attempt at unifying
everything is thwarted, right? And things are distributed. But then when they're out there
distributed, right, God has pulled himself back away from humanity. See humanity won't be destroyed.
He appoints these angelic beings, right, to govern and shepherd the nations. But the, those nations
start worshipping them and start worshipping other spirit spirits instead of God, right? And so the
the time.
coming when God is going to take revenge on those demonic spirits who have deceived the nations.
Yeah, and put things back the way they're supposed to be. Right. And that's sort of the
arc here in Deuteronomy 32. And we're also going to quote again, we've put it before on the show,
but it's going to be relevant as we go forward tonight. So we're going to just reference it
against people who have it fresh in their minds. This is the comment in Deuteronomy chapter 4 verse 19.
Okay, yeah, so do run me 419.
Beware less you
raise your eyes to heaven. And when you see the sun and the moon and the stars, all the host of heaven,
you be drawn away and bowed down to them and served them. Things that the Lord, your God, has allotted
to all the peoples under the whole heaven. So, yes, this repetition of don't engage in idolatry,
and it's this connection, of course, with the gods, with the host of heaven, the angelic beings, with
with astronomical bodies, right?
And there's this reference to this allotment of all the peoples under the whole heaven. So it's kind of yeah, yeah, exactly all the nation. So this is the this is the flip side.
Yeah, so don't because Israel is specially created by the way they got of Israel for himself.
Right.
One of the worst things they could do is for them to be like the nations and start worshiping those other.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
Because they're the ones who have sort of...
direct access to God most high through whom he intends to save those other nations.
Yeah, so before we move forward with some other really interesting quotes that you folks probably out there haven't heard before,
we actually have a caller calling in who has a question that's relevant to this.
And that is a guy with a name that is very similar to yours. His name is Stephen Young.
Can you believe it? Stephen Young. Stephen, are you there?
Yeah, I'm here. I am thrilled. I came for the Giants, a Stave for the Theology.
Absolutely loved it, Bill. Are you the former quarterback for the San Francisco 49ers?
No, but that was my dad's favorite quarterback and my brother's name is Neil Young,
which was his favorite singer. I hope people remember it all comes together.
It's exciting.
May you have other brothers named Crosby still.
and Nash. Please say yes. I wish I did. Okay. Okay. All right. We're not going to require that
of you. Stephen, what is your question, comment, concern, accusation? My question is, so obviously
have the sons of God's over the Summity Nation. Summity Nations. What is to be said about the
nations that were out.
like that weren't listed, you know, like, and obviously what I understand is on nation states
more like, you know, different ideas than that. But what about the other parts of the world? Did they also have
divine being over them, or is it just like it was these, and then they just kind of spread out
across the world and the, of course, the being still looked after them wherever they went? How, how
I mean, so I mean, least the way that the scripture depicts it is that this is the
origin of all humanity because these are the people descended from Noah and his sons.
Right. So what the scripture is saying is that this is everybody. Right. That there aren't other nations out there.
Now, is it possible that if the flood was not truly, truly worldwide that there are other nations out there?
I don't know, but I mean, that's not what that's not the picture that the scripture is giving, but I do think that even if they're
our other nations out there, which again, I don't know, that's just not the Bible story,
that they're included in this exact same dynamic, you know, because if there was some
nation out there that remained truly faithful to God, then there would have been no point
in creating Israel. Right? Why would God have needed to do that? I don't know, Father,
do you have anything you wanted to add or correct or actually?
This is Alex explain what I said that that's seven
is a symbolic number, right? The idea is that seven, right, represents the whole or completion.
And this is because there are seven planets counting the Sun and the Moon.
I'm not being facetious. That's the mind of ancient people. There were seven planets, including
the Sun and the Moon. And so seven is used. This is where what we now call the menorah comes from,
Right, the candle...
stand that was in the temple and the tabernacle that we have on our altar in
Orthodox churches. The reason there's seven lamps is that there were seven
lights in the heavens and the sun to moon and the five planets. And so that
represents sort of the whole, it's sort of a representation of microcosm,
right, literally, of the cosmos.
And so the reason why the number is set...
70 is not because just objectively there happened to be 70 nations in the world at the time,
it's to convey the whole world.
Right.
That makes sense.
And St. Matthew does something similar to this in his genealogy of Christ where he has
the 14 generations and then the 14 generations and the 14 generations.
is like six sevens and then he and then Christ
is beginning the seventh, seventh, right?
And sort of bringing it all to completion, right?
If you compare his genealogy to the genealogies of the Old Testament, in order to get 14,
14, 14, he has to edit a little bit.
Right?
I getcha.
But he's wanting to use that symbolic number to convey that meaning.
So that's why they kept it to 70, right?
If the writers could have listed more, they kept it to...
70 to convey that the whole thing. And if you look at the, there's a Romanian icon that
I know we've posted the, the JPEG of several times that depicts this. It shows sort of these
people from different nations walking away from the tarot bable with angels sort of surrounding
their head. And that icon includes a person who's clearly supposed to be Chinese and some
other people from other nations that aren't listed.
in the in Genesis 10.
Yeah, there's a need of American
need that icon.
Yeah.
So is that answer your questions,
Stephen?
Yeah, that absolutely does.
And I was atheist for most of my life.
And if I would have found orthodoxy earlier on,
I would have I would have come on board
way earlier just to make so infinitely more sense
than the common Protestantism that I was hearing
in America.
Bless you both and have a fantastic night.
Thank you very much.
All right, moving forward, let's talk about Plato.
See, not everything is Plato brain.
There's some good things to say about Plato.
Yeah, I have to tease Plato a bit at the end of this.
But anyway, what's he gonna do about it?
Um, he's cool with it either way.
Yeah, I'm a particular person.
He doesn't care about me.
No.
So this
idea that the nations were divided by the Most High God and that sort of the
spirits who govern those nations were sort of assigned to them is not
something you only find in the Bible. This is pretty much how the pagan saw it
working also. And Play-No is a really good example.
us. And so we're going to go through a couple quotes from Plato where he talks about this in two
different places. The first one is in the critis, which the critis is the place where Plato talks
about the antideluvian civilization for Plato that's atlannis, which is this great advanced civilization
before it gets destroyed by a flood. How about that? Okay, so this is the critis, a quote from
Section 1.
9, B through D. In the days of old the gods had the whole earth distributed among them
by allotment. There was no quarreling. There was no quarreling. For you cannot rightly
suppose that the gods did not know what was proper for each of them to have, or knowing
this, that they would seek to procure for themselves by contention that which more properly
belongs to others. They all of them by just apportionment obtained what they wanted and
people to their own districts.
And when they had people them, they tended us, their nurslings and possessions.
As shepherds tend their flocks, accepting only that they did not use blows or bodily
forces, shepherds do but governed us like pilots from the stern of the vessel, which
is an easy way of guiding animals, holding our souls by the rudder of persuasion according
to their own pleasure, thus did they guide all mortal creatures.
Now different gods had their allotments in different places which they set in order.
Her face is an Athena.
who are brother and sister and sprang from the same father, having a common nature and
being united also in the love of philosophy and art, both obtained as their common portion
this land, which was naturally adapted for wisdom and virtue.
And there they have implanted brave children of the soil and put into their minds the order
of government.
Their names are preserved, but their actions have disappeared by reason of the destruction
of those who received the tradition and the laps of ages.
he's talking
about, you know, Athens. He's talking about Greece, right? Which it's such as he
says are, what is it? Naturally adapted for wisdom in virtue. Yeah, Athens is. Yeah, yeah,
right. Supposed to, you know, there's no good Spartans and stuff, right?
But yeah, this isn't Spartans. Notice also what he's saying about there was no quarreling,
right? Or that they, they were gentle shepherds and all this, right? He's making these
These distinctions speak.
because those distinctions are referring to this golden age.
Yeah.
This is the way things used to be.
Right?
So now, right, Plato knew the Iliad was out there, right?
Now the gods go to war with each other over territory.
Right?
Now the gods are gentle is not a good descriptor
many of the Greek gods and the feelings with humanity.
right? Not even a little bit. Right. As we will see next time. So he's referring to this
previous golden age, there was this period of time when these spirits were apportioned
out to the day she had we had ours and they were gentle and they didn't fight and everything
was wonderful. But something has changed right for play now. The other place where he talks about
this is in his discourse on the laws.
And I know the play no fans out there, the ones that still remain who didn't get mad at me and stop listening.
Don't our fans of the law is either because it's generally regarded to be the last thing that played a wrote and did not be very good.
And to probably be unfinished.
But the particular piece that we're going to read is another place where he talks about this same thing, the same idea.
same golden age and what it's like.
All right, so this is Plato again.
I must do as you say.
Well, then tradition tells us how blissful was the life of men
in that age, furnished with everything in abundance,
and of spontaneous growth.
And the cause thereof is said to have been this.
Chronos was aware of the fact that no human being,
as we have explained, is capable of having
irresponsible control of all human affairs
without becoming filled with pride and injustice.
So pondering this fact, he then appointed as kings
and ruler.
for our cities, not men, but beings of a race that was nobler and more divine, namely demons.
He acted just as we now do in the case of sheep and herds of tame animals. We do not sit
oxen as rulers over oxen or goats over goats, but we who are of a nobler race ourselves rule over them.
In like manner the God in his love for humanity, set over us at that time the nobler race of demons,
who, with much comfort to themselves and much to us, took charge of us and furnished peace and...
monastic and orderliness and justice without stint, and thus made the tribes of men free from
feud and happy. And even today this tale has a truth to tell, namely that wherever a state has a mortal
and no god for ruler, there the people have no rest from ills and toils. So good old Plato,
not a big fan of democracy. Yeah, right. Yes. Some beings get to rule because they're just better.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, you wouldn't have an ox lead an ox with you
Right, but so you can see here. This is the dynamic at Kronus, right?
Zeus's father right is sort of the the most high God in this in this golden age and he
Portions out to the spirits right to lead all of these different groups of people so that they can all be happy back
of the golden
age, this leads to them all being happy and having all the things they need and everything
is wonderful. That's not where we live anymore. That's not where we live anymore. So you
see both this idea of the the apportionment, but also this kind of golden age view like the
Babylonians have and that even connected to the the the antideluvian world. So now moving
on from pl-
know. Now we'll go to a Christian. Right. This isn't something that's just sort of in the ancient
world. And then Christians just kind of, you know, babble on whatever, right? God's
adations are demon, sure, whatever. This is still important when we get into the, an important idea
once we get into early Christianity and
as just one example, St. Dionysius the area opa-guite talks about this in his celestial hierarchies.
Okay, so this is St. Dionysius. He says,
hence the word of God, and that's capital W, everybody, the word have God has assigned our hierarchy
to angels by naming Michael as ruler of the Jewish people and others over other nations.
for the most high established borders of nations according to the number of the angels of God.
to a Raltami 32 reference there.
But if anyone should say,
how then were the people of the Hebrews alone conducted
to the supremely divine illuminations?
We must answer that we ought not to throw
the blame of the other nations wandering after those
which are no gods upon the direct guidance of the angels,
but that they themselves by their own declension
fell away from the direct leading towards the divine being
through self-conceit and self-will
and through their irrational veneration for things
which appeared to them worthy of God.
Even the Hebrew people are said to have suffered the same thing,
for even over the other nations from whom we also have emerged,
certain not alien gods were want to preside,
yet there is one head of all, and to this the angels,
who religiously conduct those who follow them.
So he's sort of placing the blame on the nations,
and not on the angels that governed them.
you still there, do we do? Yeah. I am. You cut out for us. Oh, okay. It's a still big
pause.
All right.
Before panicking.
I was I was like, oh, oh, technical difficulties again.
Oh, our nemesis. See. Yeah.
I mean, so what's that bit about certain not alien gods write. What does
you mean? Like those are the gods that were assigned to them. They weren't from
more else. Is that what he means by that? Right.
that there are two things that happen here.
So St. Dinesius wants to make clear
that God didn't like assign the nations to demons.
So what he's not saying is that,
oh yeah, God intended for them to worship Zeus
and for these other people to worship Marduk
and these other, that's not at all.
What he intended.
that these were angels that were assigned, right?
And so in one of the next quotes we're going to read,
a lot of lengthy one, this is going to be disambiguated a little more,
but there are sort of a few different things that happen.
So in some cases, and this is in their in St. Dines as well,
the people start worshipping some other spirit other than the angel got assigned.
In some cases, that angel who was assigned to them falls and accepts their worship.
Right. And then there's probably other mixed cases, right? You've got giant spirits in there and I'll write other demonic spirits, right?
But the idea that St. Dionysius is trying to get across is that, right, again, God was not saying, okay, I'm the God of the Israelites and these demons are the gods of these other nations.
functions.
Right.
like he gave the nations to a bunch of demons, right?
He gave them away.
It wasn't interested in them, right?
That this is part of his plan toward ultimately redeeming them.
Right?
And that it's the corruption of the people
that caused this state of affairs, not God's action
that caused the state of affairs.
Right.
So yeah, and this is why then we get,
you know, these references in scripture
to all the gods of the
nations are demons, right? And then the references in St. Paul and Ephesians chapter 6 to fighting
against powers and principalities, right? And then, again, Psalm 82, which we've talked
about many times, you know, God stands up in the Council of the Gods and renders judgment.
It kind of reads off a list of charges and then destroys them at the end as he rises,
he arises from the death.
The arises to judge and inherit from all of the nations.
Right? Yeah, exactly.
That sort of the Psalm dramatizes what was already promised in Deuteronomy 32, 43,
and then of course we celebrate the fulfillment of that on Holy Saturday as Christ rises from the
dead and all authority in heaven and on earth is given to him.
Yep, yeah, exactly. So, okay, well we have another caller and we have Celeste on the line and she
wants to ask about
these fallen angels. So Celeste, are you there?
I'm here. You hear me?
Yes, we hear you. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast. Celeste, what exactly is on your mind?
Thank you. Okay. So I'm thinking about the crystallized state you first spoke about during
your first episode on the falls of men and angels. And I don't understand how if we determine
And by our own lives, whether we are so speak, go to sheep at our desk.
and Christ merely separates us.
How does praying for their pose change,
their pose from both to sheep,
and when does the crystallization happen?
All right, all right, Father Steve,
I'm gonna let you go ahead and just take this one first.
Okay, so yeah, so I thought you were gonna ask
a different question, but this question,
that's what I thought you were gonna ask.
So I'm glad this is the way you have.
Right, so...
We are able, during our lives, to repent, right, to our selves take the action of
that actions are required that lead to us being purified from sin, purified from its effects,
healing from its consequences, setting things right that we set wrong.
Once we are no longer in the body and no longer in the
this world, then we ourselves can't do that. Right. So I myself, if I pass away and I go
to Hades, in Hades, right, I can't fix what I broke, right? I can't come in and apologize
and ask forgiveness from someone, right? I can't repent and change.
right, my life, myself at that point, right?
But we have to take into account that from our perspective,
like our living human perspective,
the last judgment that sorting hasn't happened yet.
And that Christ's relationship to time
in our relationship.
to time is totally different.
Right?
And so in the same way that my prayers now might be what God uses to say, heal someone who I'm praying for.
My prayers now might be something God uses in potentially the past from my
perspective.
Right, to bring someone to repentance, to shape the course of their life.
And additionally, since that separation hasn't happened, that separation is up to Christ.
Christ is the one who judges everyone, and who makes that distinction in that separation.
People who I think look like goats may actually be sheep and vice versa.
Christ is the one who knows that. So there's a mystery here, right? And part of that mystery is that there's not sort of this bar.
Right. This is one of the differences with Western theology and Western theology. They're kind of is a bar.
Or that's the algae. There's not really a bar where you hit that bar and now you're on the saved side. And if you don't make that bar, now you're on the dam side.
And so you either have to hit that bar before you die or
or our prayers or actions need to do something to help you hit that bar after you die, but there's no bar.
Right.
Everyone is on a continuum, right, between Christ and in humanity.
And we don't know or have any basis to draw a lot of
somewhere on that continuum that says,
blessed on one side and condemned on the other.
How exactly Christ is going to do that is known only to Him.
Right? And so we all pray for each other,
and we do that continuously because all of us
need the grace of God and the support of each other,
working together to try to continue to draw closer to Christ.
They're going to become more human.
instead of less human be cleansed of our sins.
And so, the TLDR on that is you're kind of asking me how prayer for the departed works.
And there's not really a way that things work.
We just know that it does.
Right, there's not like a mechanism that we can get at of how it works.
But we know that our prayer for the departed is a continued expression of our unity.
with each other, right, and and a continued manifestation and furthering of our union with Christ.
Yeah, right. And even if it doesn't, even if it doesn't quote unquote work, right,
even if our prayers for someone who's departed end up in the final analysis and made this not be so,
but even if it ends up in the final analysis, that we just really loved and prayed with tears
for people who end up...
not loving God. Well, that makes us a lot more like Christ because we're told that God wills that none should perish.
And so Christ Himself desires the salvation of a whole bunch of people who won't have it. Don't want it.
Does that make sense to us? Does that help?
It was an awesome answer. Thank you very much.
Great. It's always good when your awesome father Steven. Thank you for coming.
So less good to hear from you tonight. Thanks for waiting by the way. Thank you very much for waiting
All right
Moving forward
Everybody's favorite semi-arion from the fourth century
You see via
Now I'm gonna think
Do you have a be of one that's more favorite? I don't know. I got a
I don't keep the four-sistery ad
Yeah, cuz my favorite semi-arion is phylo of Alexandria
Right, he's...
for some of these ranking things, right?
Like somebody asks, whose your favorite Nazi?
It's always gonna be Martin Heidegger, right?
You try and go back on that, and it gets really tough,
because you have to try and think of another Nazi
that's at all worthwhile.
Right, girl, should we?
I don't know.
Anyway, that ought to get me canceled if everything else does today.
Right, but yeah, so yeah, probably, okay, I'll give you
You see the successor.
favorite semi-arion of the fluke. It's better than you see me as a Nicaridia.
Right. Yeah, not that guy. So yeah, I mean, you see me as a
physician, of course, is mostly known as a church historian. That's his kind of
mean value to the church, right? But he has some other writings, including one
called the demonstration of the gospel. And we're going to go through a kind of a
long quote from that, which I'm going to read parts of it to you. And then
and father's Stephen will stop me and we'll talk about bits here and there.
Okay.
Well, and so why are we doing this?
Yes, yes.
People out there will be going,
why?
Why are you doing this?
The reason why is,
I've referred to this text a bunch.
I've referred to it on the show.
I've referred to it in a religion of the apostles.
I've referred to it in a bunch of places.
I'm pretty convinced no one has actually looked it up
and read it.
Just why not many times I've referred to it.
And this is worth knowing about.
for reasons we'll-
as we go through. Also, last time I talked about, when I was talking about saying a gustan
and the expulsion from Paradise and quote unquote, V-fall, right, I mentioned this text again
because I said, you know, different authors, early Christian authors, will tend to focus on one of the,
what we're calling the three falls. We'll tend to focus on one of them and make that one sort of
it, right, the main thing, right?
Even though they'll acknowledge the other ones. So for
example, St. Augustine famously in this had a vast
effect on Western theology, focuses everything in on the
expulsion from paradise, sin gets attached, everything gets
attached to that. But he also, as we talked about last time,
Cain is a fundamentally important figure to sit the city of
God. So he doesn't like deny this other stuff outright. Right?
It's just, you think so one is the main focus.
So UCB is a cesarea, specifically in this lengthy quote,
we're going to work our way through now.
He is making the Tower of Babel, the big event.
Yeah.
He's not denying the expulsion for paradise.
He talks about it.
He's not denying the flood.
But for him, the big fall, the capital F fall
is here at the Tower of Babel episode.
Right.
And just as a note, folks, just
As we quoted Plato who's not a Christian and did not say, you know, he's some kind of
church father.
When we quote, you see, he's of Ciceroia, we are not saying.
And so therefore he's a saint and infallible, you know, we're saying here is a witness to
this view.
That's the words that, yeah, I just compared semi-areans to Nazis.
Right.
I am not promoting semi-areans.
Or the tenants of national socially just to be clear.
I don't know it is Anita.
I do kind of like Heidegger, but for other reasons.
Yes, yes.
Yes, right.
Radically different reasons.
Yes, exactly, exactly.
All right, okay.
So, let's begin with from UCB's text, Demonstration of the Gospel.
Into this truth, Moses, the first mystic theologian, initiated the Hebrews of old saying,
ask thy father and he shall announce to the Thine elders, and they shall tell thee, when
the most high divided the nations when he distributed the sons of Adam.
He set the bounds of the nations according to the number of the angels of God.
His people Israel became the portion of the Lord.
Israel was the line of his inheritance.
In these words, surely he named, by the way, that's Deuteronomy 32, 8 and 9 that he just quoted from the Greek.
Yeah.
In these words, surely he names first the most high God, the supreme God of the universe.
And then as Lord, his word, whom we call Lord in the second degree after the God of the universe,
there's a semi-Aryanism.
Yeah.
Just warning sign number one.
Yeah, there you go.
And their import is that all the nations and the sons of men,
here called sons of Adam,
were distributed among the invisible guardians of the nations,
that is the angels, by the decision of the Most High God
and his secret counsel unknown to us.
Whereas to one beyond comparison with them,
the head and king of the universe,
I mean to Christ himself,
as being the only begotten Son,
was handed over that part of humanity, denominated-
Jacob and Israel, that is to say the whole division which has vision and
piety. Which means yeah exactly yeah there's so if you can if you remember the
quote from St. Dionysius the area opa guy St. Dionysius references Daniel in which
right it talks about the the Prince of Persia right and the Prince of Greece
and then they say and Michael your Prince right so he references the fact
that say Michael the Archangel was the sort of guardian angel of Israel.
And you may have just noticed that you see,
because it says that Jesus is the one who's appointed.
Right. So there's another,
another bit of semi-Aryanism,
but that's not the point of,
that's not why we're recording this,
but we're just pointing that out.
Those are some big,
problematic passages just quickly.
Right. What makes him a semi-Aryan and not a full on Aryan?
The distinction.
here is that for him we cut out we're not reading, obviously this is going to be a long quote,
but this isn't even all of book four of the demonstration of the gospel.
So at the beginning of book four he talks more about the relationship between the Father and the
Son. And so and that's why he says here that that can at the same time sort of equate Jesus
with the Archangel Michael and say that Christ is
beyond comparison with the angels is that he believes that essentially that Christ came
into being but was not created. He believes he came into being from the essence of the
Father. Yeah, but that he came into being within time. Weird. Yeah. That's what makes him
a semi-arion. And that's why I file a
of Alexandria, the Jewish author is basically a semi-arion because he believes that the logos and the spirit
were sort of made by God out of himself.
Rather than be created the way other things were created but still come into being within time. So that's why he's a semi-arion.
He is wrong.
Right. Yeah.
But this is not nice in Christology.
But even though his Christology is not what we would want, right,
It's important to see here again that at East East citing Deuteronomy, right, that these ideas, these traditions are current in the fourth century in Christianity.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, okay moving forward.
More UCBS from the same passage,
But the Angel Guardians and Shepherds of the other races allowed them
in as much as they were not able with their mind to see the invisible,
nor to ascend so high through their own weakness,
to worship things seen in the heavens, the sun and moon and stars.
For these indeed, being the most wonderful of the things of the phenomenal world,
invited upwards the eyes of those who see and as near as possible to heaven,
being as it were in the precincts of the King's court,
as near as possible to heaven, being as it were—
sorry, I'm repeating myself—
manifesting the glory of him that is the source of all by the analogy of the
vastness and beauty of created visible things, for in exhorting the portion of the Lord to grasp
with clear mind and pure soul that which is known to the mind only and unembodied, he prohibits
all terror of the things seen in heaven, adding that the Lord that God has divided them for all the
nations. He says he prohibits that terror. He means don't worship those things in heaven.
Yeah, right. And that's Deuteronomy 419. Right. Right. Exactly. And it is worth realizing why he's
He says that they were divided.
Since unseen by us, they that bear the earthy and demonic nature are everywhere wanderers,
flying through the air around the earth, unknown and undistinguished by men, and the good
spirits and powers, and indeed the divine angels themselves are ever at variance with
the worse, there was but one way for those who failed of the highest religion of the Almighty
to prosper, namely to choose the best of things visible in heaven.
But there was no slight danger, less...
seeking after God and busy with the unseen world, they should turn towards the opposing demonic powers amid the stress of things obscure and dark.
Such was their position. Notice, notice, um, he makes these references to earthy and demonic nature. Yeah. Right. So just to clarify what that is.
Remember the word Yante's giants in Greek literally means one's born of earth, one's born of gay. Yeah, actually. Right. Because that's where they come from.
game.
like the goddess, the earth, right? So he's distinguishing there, the demonic would be fallen angels,
the earthy would be basically the spirits of dead giants, right? So you have this overarching
category of unclean spirits, right? And he's just sort of distinguishing these two types.
Yeah, when he mentions these earthy spirits, that's what he's talking about.
Yeah, okay. All right, moving forward. I'm going to lose my place here.
This is translated as such. Yeah, yeah.
Yes, such. Yeah, yeah. So, okay, while those on the side of the opposing rebel power
were either demons or vile spirits immersed more or less in wickedness, I love that
life. They're immersed more or less in wickedness.
with the cunning ruler of them, all the, the, the
Cunning.
ruler of them all, the mighty demon, who first failed of their reverence of the divinity
and fell from their own portion. That's the devil. When envy of man's salvation drew them the
contrary way, plotting with all sorts of evil devices against all the nations, and even against
the Lord's portion in their jealousy of the good. Right. So notice the envy and jealousy language
about the devil. Yep. Yep. Right. In motivating his fall. And how he says, he decides to go
F.
the nations, the Semini nations, and even after Israel itself, right? Which he's calling the
Lord's portion. Yeah. Yeah. All right. These are the words of God's antagonist, boasting in the
strength of his wickedness, as he threatens to steal and obliterate the divisions of the nations,
delivered by the most high to the angels, and loudly cries that he will spoil the earth and shake
the whole race of men and change them from their former good order. And in this way, go ahead.
Let me add there.
So it's when you said these are the words.
So believe it or not, I know this is long.
They were reading through.
It's actually way longer.
I cut out little bits.
And the bit that was cut out before these are the words is actually he quoted Isaiah.
He quoted the devil in Isaiah saying that he would remove the boundaries of the nations.
Yeah.
Right.
And dispoiled the whole earth.
And so he lit on that, removed the boundaries of the nations, right?
The order that got established after Bable.
wants to destroy that order.
Yeah.
So that's why the next thing is says, and in this way he took the whole world and held it
captive and obliterated the boundaries of the nations.
I mean, this is this imperial drive.
Right.
The idea of empire, right?
You obliterate those boundaries, unite everything under yourself.
Yeah.
And from that day forward he ruled all men with deceit and the evil demons were arrayed
under their king in every place in city and land.
And thus the
whole of human life was enslaved by earthly powers and evil spirits. Instead of the earlier
ministers of God, they that were their guardian angels before were unable to defend in any way
the subject nations now involved in such a flood of evil. They took care of the rest of the
created world. They guarded the other parts of the cosmos and served according to their want
the will of God, the creator of all. But they did not realize the fall of mortal men
through the undetermined human choice of evil.
Right, so...
there he makes the same point say a St. Dionysius did, right, that it's humans who caused everything to
go bad, right? And he says that the angels who remained faithful to God sort of weren't able to
do anything about this, right? So those other angels had to sort of retreat to take a care of other
parts of the cosmos, right? That were still obedient to God, like everything other than humans.
Yeah, there's this
tradition I know of amongst Greek Orthodox Christians that maybe exists in other places too,
but I've always heard this from Greeks, that when the angelic rebellion began, that the
Archangel Michael said stop.
And which is why anyone, and I know we have at least one listener out there named Stamatius,
which is comes from the Greek word that means stop.
which is why someone named Stamatio.
So their name day is the Feast of the Archangels.
So it's this idea of like they can't make the demons stop.
They just, they're gonna do what they're gonna do.
Right, yeah.
And so they have to, right, but,
and this is a theme a lot in the Psalms is that, right,
you know, the stars all stay in their courses.
And, right, all of the sort of elements
of the natural world, all sort of what Bay God's commands,
it's just humans who are the problem.
Yeah
And so that's sort of part of the idea here is that the angels go and start taking care of everything other than the humans
because the humans are so rebellious and wicked they can't do anything.
Yeah, yeah.
All right, moving on.
We're for a great, sorry,
we're for a sickness, great and hard to heal overcame all on the face of the earth.
The nation is being driven now one way, now another by the evil spirits and falling into a depthless abyss of evil.
You know some thought it good to feast on the
of their dearest, like wild beasts that devour the raw flesh of men, and to lie shamelessly
with mothers, sisters, and daughters to strangle their old men and cast their bodies to the
dogs and birds. Why should I recall the cruel and terrible human sacrifices of the gods?
I mean, the evil demons into which they madden the human race.
Right. So these things see lists aren't just horrible things, right? You may recognize them from
giant stuff, right? Yes.
Right. It's the stuff that jives it, but these are the pointers not just that they did these horrible acts of murder and incest and and
Human sacrifice but that all of these things were related to right the strangling of people casting their bodies into animals or into bogs
Right, these are all things that these demonic spirits demanded as sacrifices from the nations, right?
These these demons that they were worshipping as gods
Here I am.
All right.
We're getting close to the end, everybody.
But it was when evils of such magnitude had fallen on the whole world from the wicked
and vile spirits and their king, and none of the guardian angels was able to defend them from the evils,
that he, God the Word, the Savior of the universe, by the goodwill of his father's love to man,
that the human race so dear to him might not be seethe in the Gulf of Sin, sent forth at last some
few and watery rays of his own light.
through the prophet Moses and the godly man before and after him, providing a cure for the
evil in man by the holy law. These and many other holy teachings and commands God the word gave
to them of old by Moses has delivering the elementary truths at the entry of the life of holiness
by means of symbols and worship of a shadowy and external character in bodily circumcision and
other things of that kind which were completed on the earth. But since as time went on,
none of the
prophets who succeeded Moses had the power to cure the evils of life owing to the excess
of wickedness and the activity of the demons daily waxed greater so that even the Hebrew
race was hurried along in the destruction of the goddess, at last the Savior and physician
of the universe comes down himself to men, bringing reinforcement to his angels for the
salvation of men, since the Father had promised him that he would give him this boon.
So that's why according to Eusebius, this is why Christ comes into the world to deal with this big demon problem.
Right. Because...
So the way he presents the Torah and the Old Testament scriptures, but specifically the Torah,
is that this comes... first of all, it comes from Christ, according to Eusebius,
but that he gives it into the world to try and preserve...
right, his portion to preserve Israel, right from
Right, what the demons have done to all the nations.
But the Torah is powerless to sort of take care of this demon problem.
At best, it could kind of preserve Israel as this sort of little bastion.
But it can't solve the problem at all.
Not only could it not solve the problem, but Israel didn't keep it.
And so they more and more started falling under this way of the same-
demonic experience. Right? And so the only solution, this is here the gospel as you see
B.S.E. is that Christ comes to defeat those demons and liberate the nations. Amen.
All right. Well, with that, we're going to take our second break and we will be right back
in just a second. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in
moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits. Give them a call.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Secret Turning, a collection of short stories by Stephen Signari. So I'm out in the
lot of order heaven and up comes father known from behind.
Grabbs me, gives me a kiss.
and tells me he's happy to see me.
Wearing his worn out, dungery bib overalls with the beat-up straw stets and pulling his
wire basket, going shopping on the avenue.
How old is now him anyway?"
Sharky asked.
Older than he acts, lefty said.
To be ready, he said, yeah, and younger than he seems.
So he says to me, Theodery.
The church is much better when you're there.
It's not the whole family when we don't see you.
You know, God misses His children.
And none all go Mrs. Her Son.
Now available in paperback, ebook and audiobook
at store.engineface.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
All right, welcome back.
just a third.
third half of our third episode in this three-part series on the Fall of Man. We're talking
about the Tower of Babel and everything that happened as a result of that.
Okay. Well, our friend Aristotle told us that everything that comes in threes is perfect.
Oh, so this maybe we should just end the entire show. The entire podcast.
This is therefore the perfect episode.
Yeah, it's a third of it.
And this is the perfect.
half of that episode, because it's the third one.
The third half of the third episode.
Exactly.
Have we done a three series?
Is this the third series?
I don't know.
I have a check, actually.
We'd have had a few series though.
So all right.
Extra perfect.
Extra most perfect.
The third of thirds.
So all right, well, in our first half,
we talked about the Tower of Babel in the city of Babel, Babylon,
itself and then the second half we talked about.
about the gods of the nations, right?
These allotment of the nations and the downfall of them
and how Christ came among other things to defeat them, right?
So, all right, so how are we going to wrap this one up,
one up, Father?
Where can we go from here?
Well, we're going to talk about now another set of allotments
that it turns out are related.
And that is the LAN.
lotments in the Torah, which I know is everybody's favorite part of the Pentateuch.
Oh yeah, big time. But mainly just the people who published Bible maps. Yeah.
It's like the geography chapter in the Silmarillion. No one loves that chapter except for the people
who make their own maps of Belirian. Yeah. A cartography people, man. Dude out there is an expert
on 16th century maps. Yeah, yeah.
I mean, I love that stuff.
I always loved cartography when I was young.
Yeah.
I always pulled out the maps from the National Geographic
and put them on my walls.
This is the thing with academia, man.
If you want to study, you could spend your whole life studying
late antique Roman textiles, right?
16th century maps, right?
Whenever you're into, man.
That's perfectly legitimate if that's
what you wanted to vote your life to.
but we're not gonna all play ball.
It's like relevant to anything.
Yeah.
You do you.
Oh, come on, man.
You do you, whatever you do, man, it's cool.
But 16th century maps probably would not work as a pitch
for a new podcast in ancient faith radio.
I don't know.
I can kind of come on in audio podcasts.
Yeah.
Describing maps in that audio world.
and 33 degrees to the north.
West. Yeah, it's the top that looks like New Jersey and then like follow like. All right,
enough digression. All right, land allotments. Yeah. And by the way, yes, we're just saying we will
never do an episode of the Piriora's map. So land allotments in the Torah, right? So probably the
the more well-known of those.
And I say more purely as a comparative.
It would be the pieces of land within Canaan
that were allotted to the different tribes.
And I say that purely as a comparative,
because, again, not a lot of people
jumping up and down with love for the book of numbers.
But there were particular pieces of land designated
for each tribe, right, in the area of Cane.
and even if you've never poured over the maps that get produced of this of where they were supposed to be,
you may be aware of that.
You may also be aware of the fact that the Levites did not get a piece of land.
The Levites' inheritance, their allotment, has got himself, right?
And that was a way of conveying what we've talked about before that in Israel,
concentric circles.
Right? And the closer you are to God, like the higher level of purity you had to maintain.
Right? So Israel was called to a higher level of purity than the nations. And then the priesthood
within Israel was called to a higher level of purity than the rest of Israel. And then the high
priest is called the highest level of pure. Because how close they were going to be to the
the presence of God. Right? But so they have an allotment. It's just not land. Right? And so they
their food and clothing and support from the people of the other tribes when they came to worship and offer sacrifices.
But these these allotments and the boundaries of these allotments are considered by the Torah to be set in stone.
meaning that hypothetically every 50th year when you get to a Jubilee year, right?
So every seven years you have a Sabbath year and then after
seven sevens you have the 50th year. That's the Jubilee year. One of the things that happens in the Jubilee year is that all of the land reverts back to the the tribes and
clans that originally had those alopments.
This big big resetting of all the boundaries and anyone who rented a property or brought a property it goes back back to these original boundaries and this original order.
Now, we know from the text of the Old Testament that Israel never actually did this.
There was never a single Jubilee year, right? That they actually celebrated. They didn't even ever do the Sabbath year.
Wow. And we know that because Jeremiah gets told that the reason the exile was going to last for 70 years is that Israel had been in the land for 490 years and it never celebrated the Sabbath year.
So God was taking all 70 of his Sabbath years at once. Wow, that they owed him. Wow.
So, and if they weren't doing the Sabbath year, they definitely weren't doing Jubilee, right?
But, so those are some less well known because for various reasons related to the beliefs
of certain segments of American evangelical Christianity, we think we only think about
Israel when we think about this.
descendants of Abraham, this included, there were land allotments made by God to the other descendants of Abraham.
So, so, edomites, some other people, edomites, moabites, ammonites.
Okay.
And if you don't believe me, or you're just interested in reading more about it, go to Deuteronomy chapter two.
The edomites are mentioned in and around verse 5.
the Moabites are mentioned in and around verse 9. The Ammonites are mentioned in and around verse 19.
It's reiterated there that obviously the Idomites are descended from Esau, but the Moabites and the
Ammonites are descended from Lot. Abraham's nephew, part of his family. And in all three cases, as the
Israelites are approaching Canaan to take the land that he's allotted to them, at least in theory,
Uh,
God says you're not to touch these people.
You're not to touch their land.
You don't get a single foot of it.
Yeah.
I just looked at the verses and it's basically like,
don't invade them.
Don't harass them because I gave them that land.
Right.
God gave them that land and part of him giving them that land, right?
He allots them the land and then what they're required to do is to go in and drive out
the giant clans.
If you read in Deuteronomy chapter two and all three of those kids.
places it then lists the giant clans who are driven out before those Abrahamites.
Right. The Philistines are also included in there even though they're Greek.
But that's a whole other thing. All the Greeks in Israel, we'll talk about it another time.
So, uh, but so that the idea is, right, and this is part of where the folks I mentioned a few minutes ago, stop.
is that they look at the promises to Abraham regarding the land and it's this huge swath of land.
And they say, well, Israel never had all that land.
But again, reclosely, that land, big swath of land, wasn't promised to Israel.
It was promised to Abraham's descendants.
And if you put together all of these land allotments, guess what you find out?
Yeah
That's the borders.
That's where it went.
And so Israel are the late comers, right?
When they show up in Taynan, in Deuteronomy,
at the end of the 40 years of wandering in the wilderness,
these other Abrahamites already have their land.
They've already driven out the giants, so they already have their land.
So now it's up to them, and this is what the book of Joshua is about.
It's up to them now to go and take their allotments and drive out the giants,
about the Giants.
for them. And even though a bunch of the tribes don't go to their
allotments, they go somewhere else like Dan or they don't
completely take the land they're supposed to take, or they
let some of the giants get away, right? Even though they do
all that when we get to the end of Joshua, the book of
Joshua says that all those land promises were fulfilled.
Hmm.
Yeah, no matter how much you're standing, they're all fulfilled.
Right. It's been done. Like this is not something in the future. Yeah. So like Joshua 11, 23.
So Joshua took the whole land according to all that the Lord had spoken to Moses.
And Joshua gave it for an inheritance to Israel according to their tribal allotments
and the land had rest from war. And then Joshua 21 versus 43 through 45. Thus the Lord gave to Israel
all the land that he swore to give to their fathers. And they took possession of it. And they settled
there.
and the Lord gave them rest on every side just as he had sworn to their fathers,
not one of all their enemies had stood them, for the Lord had given all their enemies into their hands.
Not one word of all the good promises that the Lord had made to the House of Israel had failed all came to pass.
All the promises were fulfilled.
Right.
So there are no land promises to any ethnic nation of anybody still outstanding from the
book of Jin.
There we go. I like that. Put stars around it. Sorry to our
dispensationalist friends. Yes. Support your Palestinian brothers and sisters in
Christ. Anyway. Amen. So, right, so that's all done, right? But so what was that
about anyway? Especially since it's all done, right? Yeah. I know we've mentioned on
the show before when we were talking about Abraham that
these land promises and this is the way like say Paul's epistle to the Hebrews interprets it.
Right? Is that the land, the physical land was a sign. Right? So it's very common in prophecy
in the Old Testament, and even sometimes in the New Testament, that there is a physical and immediate
sign that people will see that serves as the guarantee that the larger profit
see will come true. Yeah, kind of down payment. Right. And so when you see this first part come true,
then you'll know that the rest of it is true. Right. So in a lot of ways, right, Genesis remembers
part of the Torah. So we get the promises to Abraham and Genesis by the end of the Torah, and if you
If you throw in Joshua's the Hexatook especially, but even if you don't.
You see the fulfillment of the sign is real coming into the land that was promised, right?
That first bar being kept. That's what you see in the Torah. The rest of the Torah is basically that being fulfilled, the sign being fulfilled.
Which then causes the Torah as a whole to function as a pointer toward the eventual fulfillment of the larger promise.
So what's the larger promise?
Well the larger promise pretty well parallel.
what happened in driving out the giant clans and receiving the allotted land, right?
Because the promise to Abraham, and it's reiterated several times.
But in Genesis 15, 5 in particular, right, it says that they will be in number,
his descendants will be in number like the sand of the sea, and they will be like the stars of heaven.
Right.
So the stars of heaven there are used qualitatively.
And we've laid this out in preview.
episodes, right? This is how Filo interprets it. But just for tonight, if you want somebody who
interprets it that way, Daniel, right, the prophet Daniel and Daniel 12 verse three, right, in
talking about the resurrection of the dead says, and those who are white, shall shine like the brightness
of the sky above. And those who turn many to righteousness like the stars forever and ever.
Yeah, so that's how he reads it. So you're obviously going to become a lot
Like the stars of heaven, which we've already seen are connected to the angelic realm.
And then Genesis 22 verse 17 adds, when those promises are reiterated, adds this extra element.
And your offspring shall possess the gate of his enemies.
And possess is the translation that got cut and pasted here.
The original Hebrew were kind of means camp and they'll dwell in the gate
of their enemies. So the gate is the place where you fend it off attacks from your city.
So if somebody is, if they're camping in your gates, you lost, but they've come in and take it
over your city. Right? Yeah. So they're going to become like the stars of heaven. They're going to
defeat these enemies, right? And so the land is this sign, the fulfillment.
The bigger promise is that the descendants of Abraham, the sons of Abraham, those who are like Abraham who are faithful,
they are going to ultimately become
gods, become like the angelic beings, become sons of God, and are going to replace
those fallen angelic beings, right? Who are the gods of the nations? They're gonna take their roles.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
So yes.
So to that end, you mentioned Filo of Alexandria earlier, so we have a quote from Filo.
And I think we've quoted this one before, but it's relevant again to what we're talking
about here.
This is from his special laws.
One part three, I don't know if that's chapter one or book one, but anyway, one part three.
Book one part three.
There you go.
Okay.
He writes this, some have supposed that the sun and moon and the other stars were gods with
absolute power.
and ascribed to them the causation of all events. But Moses held that the universe was created,
and is, in a sense, the greatest of commonwealths having magistrates and subjects. For magistrates,
all the heavenly bodies fixed and wandering for subjects such beings as exist below the moon
and the air on the earth. These magistrates, however, in his view do not have unconditional powers
but are lieutenants of the one father of all.
And it is by mimicking the example of his governance.
exercise according to law and justice overall created things that they acquit themselves
a right. So all the gods which the senses know in the heavens must not be supposed to possess
absolute power but to have received the rank of subordinate rulers naturally liable to
correction. Let us proceed to give honor to the immaterial invisible understood by the intellect
alone who is not only the God of gods, whether perceived by sense or by mind, but also the
Make a...
of all. So what the angels are doing is not just that some of them were governing the nations,
but they're governing all these aspects of the cosmos. They're part of God's sort of
administration. There's lieutenants, magistrates, yeah. Right. And so they are sort of actively engaged
with the cosmos, ruling elements of it, right, guiding elements of it. Right. They're
not capital G gods.
They're not like God in that sense, right?
But Philo, who's a Jewish person
of the first century BC, has no problem calling them gods.
Right.
I mean, it's in the Bible.
He's just using biblical language.
Right.
And so, right, this is the role that those angelic beings had.
This is the role that in which humans are going to replace them.
And we see this play out all over the place
the new test.
as theosis is described, right?
What that concretely means.
Exactly.
So in Matthew 1928 and Luke 22 verse 30,
parallel passages, the apostles received this promise
that they're going to sit on 12 thrones
and judge the 12 tribes of Israel, right?
As their reward for what they've given up, right?
The things they've given up in this life, right?
in Revelation 3, 2021.
one at the beginning of the book of Revelation,
there are these letters to the seven churches,
and each one of them sort of concludes with a promise
to the one who overcomes, right?
The one who conquers, who overcomes.
And this one, Revelation 321,
the one who conquers, I will grant him to sit with me
on my throne as I also conquered
and sat down with my father on his throne.
Does that co-ruling image again?
Right, and Revelation 4.4, right?
you see the
the 24 elders who are sitting on 24 thrones, right?
Governing.
And it's not a coincidence that there are 24 of them
because 24 is one third of 72.
Yeah, and in this case, 72 represents
the angelic governors of the nations
and so the idea is that, you know,
and as it says in Revelation 12, 4,
it says that a third of the stars fall out of heaven
because of
swept out by the tail of the dragon. Now we should say that that doesn't mean that only a third of
the nations fell. That's not what that means. The number is getting repurposed here.
Yeah, guys, don't spreadsheet this. Okay. This is not saying there's only 24 saints. This is not
saying there were exactly. There were only 24 demons who fell. Right. That's not right. Yeah.
And if there's any questions, the third, the proportion, yeah, we're trying to have the same
proportion. And there's only question in people's minds about these 24 elders, whether these are humans,
the song that they sing before the throne of God, one of the things that they say is,
you have redeemed us out of every nation. That's humans. That's only humans. That's not angels.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. And so then in both and in both Revelation 5, 10 and 20 verse 4, it talks about
those who are...
participate in the resurrection,
reigning with Christ, right? The survey is priests and reigning as kings.
Yeah, exactly. And there is also this reference in one of these verses to
those who reign with Christ wearing white garments. You see this in some, for instance,
icons of all saints. Hell, not every icon of all saints, but there are some all saints
icons in which all the saints there and the angels are all wearing these white garments.
you know so this is straight out of
the book of Revelation. And I just want to read Revelation 24 which has this stunning image,
the stunning picture painted here by the Apostle John. Then I saw thrones and seated on them were
those to whom the authority to judge was committed. Also, I saw the souls of those who had been
beheaded for the testimony of Jesus and for the Word of God and those who had not worshiped the beast
or its image and had not received its mark on their forehead or their hands.
They came to life and reigned with Christ for a thousand years.
It's just astonishing.
This beautiful, beautiful image there of what theoses is, you know, cool, cool stuff.
All right, well, to wrap up this episode, um, some final thoughts from each of us.
Um, you know, number one, we ended up on theoses, right?
which
probably you didn't think the episode about the tarot ball but what in there but here we are
because that's this is one of the big arcs of the scriptures and
Also, this is the arc of all three of these episodes is that
The fall of man is not just a tragedy
right there is hope
at the end of it and
um in the midst of all of the darkness and evil that has come into the world as a result of the events that we've described that what from the scriptures
there is hope that not just that we would be saved out of the world, right? That's not actually what it says in scripture
but rather that we would be saved from the evil one
and that's in the Lord's Prayer before he goes to his crucifixion that
those who follow him would be saved from the evil one, right? And
that means no longer under his influence. That means no longer doing his works as we talked about in the last episode
But it also means positively, not just no longer some things, but positively, it means doing
the works of the Lord, doing the works of Christ, doing the works of God as our Father.
And so we image him, therefore, right?
And so what this means is that ultimately the the telos of theosius is not is not just
Oh, we become like God in some kind of sort of
attributive sense, although that's part of it, right?
but also we become like God in terms of what he does in the world. And we see that
demonstrated for us, of course, by the angels. And we see that realized in the
saints, the saints take up this mantle that the fallen angels threw down when
they decided to disobey. Right? And so as a result, then that means that the
life of the world to come is not...
Just a bunch of glowing beings standing up on clouds or sitting on thrones and giving orders or just you know, it's not the static thing
It is dynamic because part of what it means to be created beings is that we're dynamic we change that's the way it is
But it's gonna be good change because we'll be preserved from sin at that point if we are in Christ
Right so the age to come the life the age to come is a very creative age a very creative age
You know, it's well known.
to pretty much anyone who listens to anything that I am part of or often things that I write.
That a big fan of the works of J.R. Tolkien. And I'm going to bring up something that he said
because it's very relevant to this. One of the letters that he wrote to his, one of his sons.
And I don't have the quote in front of me, so I'm going to have to paraphrase it a little bit.
But what he says is, there is a place called heaven where all the stories that are unfinished
will continue.
where all the songs that are yet to be sung will be sung.
Right? And so this is part of his vision. And I think it's
aligns very much with the scriptures and things we've talked
about that the life of the age to come will be a creative
age. It'll be creative. And not just being creativity in
terms of the kinds of things that we normally think of as
creative stuff like art and literature and so forth. There's
a creativity that every human being has that is about
Making and doing what is good, right?
And in that we imitate our father, who is the creator.
That is how he is revealed to us is the one who makes things to be, one who makes things.
He's a maker, right? So, you know, the life of the age to come is not going to be a much
of people sitting around not having a life. It will be a creative life, a building life.
It'll be life more abundant than what we have now. Like we shouldn't think of it as somehow
less because it's.
It's not. It's going to be even more than what we have now. Right?
You know, this idea that the good things that we do in this life that are in the name of
God that are in accordance with his commandments, that are faithfulness to him, that this continues
into the age that is to come. Right? So even though the things that we build and do might
seem temporary in this world, and there's a certain temporarianist to them, they also have
this eternal care.
as well, right? There's we are making permanent contributions to the New Jerusalem, right? And so
that's one way of understanding what it means for us to be saved. And I think it's a very compelling, very compelling vision
of why we should want to be Christians at all, right? It's not the only thing to say about it. It's not the only angle from which to look at it, but it is absolutely part of it.
that we take up these roles along with the angelic hosts as the scenes have already done
and we participate in the governing, the shaping, the creativity of this creation.
Father Stephen?
So we talked here and there completely non-controversially about Empire this evening.
And to reiterate, I don't know if we've iterated it on the show, but the origin of the whole concept of empire and of an emperor actually in terms of the terminology actually comes out of Rome.
Because the Romans historically had a really bad experience with kings.
That's where we get the word tyrants is from there.
early kings and sort of so their memory before the Republic of Kings was
extremely negative. So when the time came for Caesar, things didn't go so well
for Julius, he, though he did die surrounded by his friends, we can say that
about him. Wow, that was dark father.
When it came to Octavian, when it came to Augusta.
King was the last title that they were going to try to take because that would have been a step too far.
And so what they come up with is impirator. What they come up with is conqueror.
And therefore, an empire is the conquest, right? Is what has been seized, what has been taken.
and then what they can do with it.
as a conqueror. And that way of thinking isn't just something that applies at the top level of politics, right?
If you're Queen Victoria or the president of the United States or Napoleon. That way of thinking is everywhere and has been democratized in our modern human experience.
everyone
is now made into an emperor in that everyone is sent out to conquer.
You may never literally conquer the world.
In fact, odds are good, you won't.
Especially if you're listening to this.
But you can conquer some little piece of it.
You can set up some little thiefdom, and you can do it at the expense of others.
The more ruthless you are, the bigger an empire you can build for yourself.
whether it be in something like business or it be in something that most people would consider silly on the internet or something.
We can all set up our little fiefdoms. We can all try and put together a following of peasants who we consider beneath us.
We can all exploit others and exploit the world around us.
But even more so than that external temptation, right, toward others.
conquest itself, right? That idea itself is not always necessarily bad. Why do I say
that? Well, because we also saw that word in that concept briefly, when we
quoted one of the letters to the seven churches in the book of Revelation, that
terminology is used actually in all seven of them, and it's used in terms of the
promise. Depending on your trans...
It'll say to the one who overcomes or just straightforwardly to the one who conquers
To the one who conquers this will be given a white robe will be given a new name will be given
They will sit upon Christ thrown with him
The question is who or what are we conquering
and
What St. John is talking about in Revelation?
What really Christ...
those letters were dictated by Christ to St. John in the book of Revelation.
What Christ is talking about there is not setting up an empire on this earth.
Business, political, military, whatever, popularity, likes, right, as an influencer.
What Christ is talking about, we see in the quote that we actually read from the one letter
letter where he talks about the fact that he himself
conquered. And he himself conquered not the Roman Empire literally, in the sense of he
didn't go to Rome and kill Caesar and make himself Caesar. He conquered the very demonic powers
that we've been talking about all evening. So if that's what Christ did, what does it mean for us
to conquer. What are we called upon to conquer?
as Christians to be the one who overcomes the one who conquers.
Allow me to suggest that who we each need to conquer is ourselves.
This is where self-mastery comes back into the picture.
Our self, right, our soul is the territory that we need to conquer.
And to conquer it, we're going to have to drive
out the evil spirits and their influence that is taken up residents. So that means we're
going to have to, here's what that looks like. We're going to have to conquer our pride.
We're going to have to conquer our ego. You don't do that by sitting around thinking about
how horrible you are in moping. We're putting on big displays of humility. That's not conquering
pride, right? In fact, that kind of still is pride.
What conquering pride looks like is that your ego cannot make you do anything.
Someone cannot walk up to you and insult you, and thereby ruin your day, cause you to
sin against other people, cause you to want to take revenge against them.
If you've conquered your own ego, then the worst insult that can be leveled at you, you
will take as food for thought.
there's something legitimate here I can learn from.
Maybe not, but maybe there is.
Right?
It means we need to conquer our envy and our jealousy.
What does that look like?
That looks like when someone around us is rejoicing
and is happy and has had something good
and wonderful happened to them.
We're rejoicing and happy with them
as if it happened to us.
We're not bitter and angry that they got something
we didn't or didn't have or wanted.
We're not jealous.
We don't resent them, right?
But we're actually happy.
In fact, maybe even happier that it happened to them
than that it happened to us,
no matter who they are, whether we like them or not,
whether we get along with them or not.
That's what actually conquering and mastering jealousy
and envy in yourself look like.
And we can say the same about any other sin,
whether it's on the list of seven deadly sins or not, right?
Conquering ourselves, mastering ourselves
means that there is no force.
There is no passion. There is nothing outside of us that can cause us to react and to do anything.
That we are able to set our own limits, that we are able to choose to do that which we want to do in following Christ and becoming like Him.
And that's not something that you just do on a Wednesday.
Today I mastered myself. Today I conquered myself.
myself. This is a
battle that goes on throughout our entire lives. The day when we can say whether or
not we're the one who conquers is when Christ tells us so when we reach the end.
Until then we fight to purify ourselves, to purge ourselves from these dark and
We will influence us to set ourselves right.
But this is the
the positive side of repentance.
It's not about repentance, it's not about feeling bad.
It's not about moping, it's not about wearing a hair shirt.
Unless you're sitting in the hair shirt.
But repentance is about fighting back.
It's about taking back your own life and your own self
and your own soul by mastering yourself.
so that hopefully we can be those ones on the last day.
who Christ rewards with a palm branch and a white rope and a new name and
ultimately to come to share in his reign and rule over his creation. Those are my last thoughts.
Amen. Well that is our show for tonight. Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live we'd so love to hear from you. You can email us at
LordofSpuresItEachAndFaith.com. You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a
voice mail at SpeakPie.
dot com slash lord of spirits.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Usually not two weeks from now.
That one's recorded, but most of the time live broadcasts.
Second. Yep. Yep.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page.
Join our discussion group.
Leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share this show with a friend
whom you know is going to love it.
And it will be helpful to them.
I say, share it with strangers.
And finally, be sure to go to hfate.com,
stroke support, and help make sure we
and lots of other AFR podcasters stay with you.
Thank you very much.
Good night, and God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits,
orthodox Christian.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.